<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief exposition upon the second Psalme. Wherein wee have that time modestly pointed at, (by the favourable direction of that significant then in the 5th v.) in which the father will in wrath to the (professing, refined) rulers of the world set his Sonne on Sion. And a description of the work the Son then performeth, both by his spirit, and his mysticall body. With usefull observations thereupon. Tending to clear up the scope of the whole Psalme. With application to our times. / By William Llanvædonon of P.H.C.</title>
            <author>Llanvædonon, William, of P.H.C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E844_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210352</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869160</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869160</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170601</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88385)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170601)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 248:E844[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief exposition upon the second Psalme. Wherein wee have that time modestly pointed at, (by the favourable direction of that significant then in the 5th v.) in which the father will in wrath to the (professing, refined) rulers of the world set his Sonne on Sion. And a description of the work the Son then performeth, both by his spirit, and his mysticall body. With usefull observations thereupon. Tending to clear up the scope of the whole Psalme. With application to our times. / By William Llanvædonon of P.H.C.</title>
                  <author>Llanvædonon, William, of P.H.C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Livewell Chapman, at the Crowne in Popes-head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>William Llanvædonon is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 23"; "June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms II --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170601:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF EXPOSITION <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON</hi> THE SECOND PSALME. <hi>Wherein wee have</hi> That Time Modeſtly pointed at, (by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable direction of that ſignificant THEN in the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>v.</hi>) in which the Father will in <hi>Wrath</hi> to the (profeſſing, refined) RULERS of the World Set His SONNE on SION. <hi>AND A Deſcription</hi> of the work the Son then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth, both by his Spirit, and his Myſticall Body. <hi>With uſefull Obſervations thereupon.</hi> Tending to clear up the ſcope of the whole <hi>Pſalme.</hi> With Application to our Times.</p>
            <p>By WILLAM LLANVAEDONON of P. H. C.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Repent yee, for the Kingdome of Henven is at hand,</hi> Mat. 3.2. <hi>But the Saints of the moſt High ſhall TAKE the Kingdome, and POSESSE the Kingdome for ever, even for ever and ever.</hi> 
               <bibl>Dan. 7.18.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the <hi>Crowne</hi> in <hi>Popeſ-head</hi>-Alley. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170601:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170601:2"/>
            <head>THE AUTHOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is a Time wherein God will ſpeak to the Rulers of the World (the profeſſing Rulers, the Rulers in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) by<note n="a" place="margin">verſ. 11.</note> 
               <hi>A STAMMERING LIPP,</hi> a ſtuttering tongue (in the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Eſay</hi>) in ſuch a manner, as though this ſtammering lipp tell them,<note n="b" place="margin">verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>This is the Rest wherewith yee may cauſe the weary to reſt, and this is the refreſhing;</hi> though it ſhew them the way to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a ſure and certaine Reſt, to ſettle themſelves upon an everlaſting foundation, yet<note n="c" place="margin">verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>They will not heare:</hi> God withdrawes from them, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his word hath been<note n="d" place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Precept upon precept, and line upon line,</hi> it's now but <hi>here a little, and there a little</hi> among them: But although the word of God
<pb facs="tcp:170601:3"/>come forth into the world at this time in ſuch a ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering weak poſture, that it's <hi>deſpiſed and ſet at nought</hi> by the Rulers of the world, thoſe<note n="e" place="margin">verſ. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Scornfull men,</hi> yet, it's the Power of God; the breath of this <hi>STAMMERING LIPP</hi> ſmites theſe Scorners to the earth. Behold! what a Sermon of Terrors this ſtut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering tongue preacheth to theſe Rulers in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> from the 14 to the 23 Verſe. Theſe Rulers are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and hugging themſelves in their owne wayes, with their Covenants and Agreements, Aſſociations of Peace, as the moſt ſafe and unerring way to their ſettlement: Say they,<note n="f" place="margin">verſ. 15.</note> 
               <hi>We have made a Covenant with death</hi> (our ſtrongeſt enemies) <hi>and with hell</hi> (the torment of a conquered condition) <hi>are we at agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that ſhall never befall us: <hi>When the overflowing ſcourge ſhall paſſe through, it ſhall not come unto us, for we have made lyes</hi> (high pretences for God and his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for the welfare and peace of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) <hi>our refuge, and under falſhood have we hid our ſelves:</hi> As confident as theſe Rulers ſeem to be, yet this weak <hi>ſtammering lipp</hi> overcomes them, conquers them;<note n="g" place="margin">verſ. 18, 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with death ſhall be diſanull'd, and your agreement with hell ſhall not ſtand, the overflowing ſcourge ſhall overftow and tread you downe; it ſhall be a vexation to you to underſtand the report, the bed is ſhorter than that a man can ſtretch himſelfe in it, and the covering narrower than he can rap himſelfe in it:</hi> And the Lord ſhall doe this by laying <hi>in</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">verſ. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Sion for a foundation, a ſtone, a tryed stone, a pretious corner stone, a ſure foundation:</hi> Laying<note n="i" place="margin">verſ. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Judgement to the line, and righteouſneſſe to the plumet;</hi> Sending <hi>a ſhowre of haile to ſweep away the refuge of lyes,</hi> and cauſing <hi>the waters to overflow the hiding place:</hi> All your fine pretences and curious ſlights of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:170601:3"/>thoſe garniſht coverings under which you hide your evill intentions from the eyes of men, are now too narrow to hide you, you are diſcovered; thus your <hi>bed is become too ſhort</hi> for you, thoſe faire and ſpetious deſigns of yours, which you thought would prove as a bed of Downe whereon you might reſt your weary bones, are become too ſhort, that it's a become a ſufficient vexation to you to underſtand the report, the wiſedome of God in this <hi>STAMME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RING LIPP</hi> is got beyond you to your great regret and miſery: and leaſt theſe men ſhould in their hearts make it an impoſſibility, theſe things ſhould be brought to paſſe, ſaith the ſame ſtammering lipp,<note n="k" place="margin">verſ. 21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord ſtall riſe up as in Mount Perazim, he ſhall be wroth as in the valley of Gibeon, that he may doe his work, his ſtrange worke; and bring to paſſe his act, his ſtrange act.</hi> And <hi>now therefore be ye not Mockers, leſt your bands be made ſtrong, for I have heard from the Lord of Hoſts a conſumption, even determined upon the whole earth.</hi> This Meſſage God ſends to theſe Rulers by a <hi>ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering lipp (here a little, and there a little)</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>that they may goe, and fall backward, and be broken, and ſnared, and taken.</hi> There's no way to avoyd this judgement of the wrath of God, but by liſtening to theſe <hi>ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merings</hi> of the lipp, ſpelling the mind of God out of them, bending our hearts to a conformity to it.</p>
            <p>And now Courteous Reader, all my ambition is, that theſe few <hi>Meditations</hi> I here preſent thee with, may prove <hi>a piece of that ſtammering lipp,</hi> by which God ſpeaks to the world; Surely I can promſe thee no more than a <hi>company of ſtammerings,</hi> O that our Lord Jeſus would cauſe ſomething of his fathers mind to be ſpell'd out of them, that ſome glory may
<pb facs="tcp:170601:4"/>redound to his holy name! then ſhall I have my aime, and I ſhall poſſeſſe a dram of that joy which none can be able to deprive me of: Neither deſpiſe nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject them becauſe they are but <hi>ſtammerings,</hi> for you ſee by the fore-mentioned Scripture, the Lord in wrath to the worlds pretending Rulers, chooſeth <hi>a ſtammering lipp</hi> to ſpeak forth his mind to the world, ſo that if we would in ſuch a day as the Prophet makes mention of, be acquainted with the will of our God, we muſt ſit downe under the Oratory of that ſtuttering tongue; therefore how greatly doth it concern us to ſearch and try every thing, and hold faſt that which is good. I might have enlarged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly throughout the whole of this work, but upon ſeverall conſiderations I have choſen rather to hint and point at things as well as I could, than to dilate upon them. The good Lord water what hath been done with his rich bleſſing, and then a fruitfull crop of honour to our dear Lord King Jeſus will ſpring forth: The God and Father of our Lord grant it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170601:4"/>
            <head>MEDITATIONS On the SECOND PSALME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Pſalmiſt <hi>David,</hi> that ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was a man after Gods owne heart (as is elſwhere teſtified of him) and God knowing that he would make ſuch an improvement of the diſcoveries of what he would doe in the world, as would be very ſuitable to the heart of God; according (as he dealt with his Father <hi>Abraham</hi> of old, and) to his Promiſe, he keeps not his ſecrets from him, but reveales to him things to come, what he would doe in the laſt dayes; a Conference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Father and the Son, concerning the great intereſt of his Son, (the ſum of which is this ſecond <hi>Pſalme</hi>) wherein the father expreſſes ſo great love, and manifeſts ſuch ſtrong reſolutions, to exerciſe his wiſedome and power in doing that for his Son, which his love tells him becomes the love of ſuch a father to performe, and his deare Son doth deſerve. The Son ſeeing his Father ſo full of wrath and jealouſie for his ſake, going about to make bare the arme of all his wonderfull At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, and ſet them all on work to bring to paſſe his Decree concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his beloved; he ſteps in, declares the Decree to the Sons of men, and he doth it with ſuch tenderneſſe of heart, ſuch loving exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and invitations, that if poſſible he might perſwade them to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his Scepter, come under his healing wings, and be bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p n="1">In this Pſalme we have</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170601:5"/>
            <div type="section">
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, A TIME pointed at.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, WORKE to be done in that time; which is double. <hi>The worke of God,</hi> and the <hi>Worke of Christ</hi> the Son.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, The MANNER of Chriſts doing his work.</item>
               </list>
               <p>We have <hi>Two times</hi> pointed at by the holy Ghoſt in this Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1 All that ſpace of time between Chriſts firſt coming in the dayes of his humiliation, and his ſecond coming in the day of his power and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to take the Kingdome to himſelfe. For the clearing up of this, conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1 That the holy Ghoſt devides the enemies which Chriſt ſhall have in this large Tract of time, into three ranks.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Heathens and People.</item>
                  <item>2 Kings of the Earth. And</item>
                  <item>3 Rulers.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Heathens and People (that is <hi>Jewes</hi>) againſt Chriſt, for that ſpace of time wherein Heatheniſh <hi>Rome</hi> bare rule. Kings of the earth, while Antichriſt Lords it over the Heritage of God. And laſtly, Apoſtate Rulers, men of more refined Principles and profeſſions (as will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in its place) that yet ſhall prove Apoſtates, ſuch pernicious impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable enemies to Chriſt in the laſt dayes, ſuch, as God ſhall be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger able to bear with, but ſhall come forth againſt them <hi>in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 And ſurely, The holy Ghoſt's diſtinct manner of Characteriſing them, ſignifies not a little to us concerning this matter. What more fit and true Character can be given of Heatheniſh <hi>Rome</hi> (that great red Dragon) than <hi>rage?</hi> What rage did that Beaſt exerciſe againſt the poore flock of Chriſt? How did he rend and teare it to pieces? The ten firſt Perſecutions witneſſe to it; And what vaine things did the people of the <hi>Jewes</hi> imagine, when they thought to extinguiſh the light of the Goſpel, that ſhone in their Horiſon, and to extirpate the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt out of their Coaſts? And ſecondly, How directly and particularly doth the holy Ghoſt point out unto us the ten Hornes that gave their power to the Beaſt, under the notion of the <hi>Kings of the earth ſetting themſelves againſt the Lord, and his anointed?</hi> How open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtoutly the Kings of the earth have ſet themſelves againſt the Lord, and his anointed, in giving their power to maintaine the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, luſts, and blaſphemies of the man of ſin, is evident by the havock they have made in the Church of Chriſt theſe many hundred yeares. And laſtly, How exact and preciſe is the holy Ghoſt in deſcribing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us by many notable Characters, the conſtitution of a third ſort of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170601:5"/>
                  <hi>Rulers,</hi> that ſhould come upon the ſtage of the world in the latter end of thoſe dayes, to finiſh the Tragedy of the old Serpent; yet, before the Kings of the earth ſhould be totally extinct, or put by from proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting their work; for while the remaining Kings of the earth ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, theſe take counſell together <hi>againſt the Lord and his anointed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 The Apoſtles and Brethren in the fourth of the <hi>Acts,</hi> are of our mind; they <hi>begin</hi> the fulfilling of this Propheſie with the firſt coming of Chriſt, when <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were gathered together againſt Chriſt, in the twenty-ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Verſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 As to the <hi>finiſhing-time</hi> of this Propheſie, we have good and ſure ground to receive it for a truth, that this Propheſie runs downe to the day of Chriſts power, when all the Kingdomes of this world ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Kingdomes of the Lords Chriſt. For,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Here's the forbearance and long-ſufferance of God at an end: He ſpeaks to the world <hi>in wrath, and vexeth them in his ſore diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> A courſe God takes not till he hath tryed all other wayes and means, and that indeed the world hath fill'd the cup of her iniquity al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt full, and the myſtery of iniquity is almoſt finiſh't; then, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to make a full end of her, as he did of the old world, when the appointed time came: But</item>
                  <item>2 Chriſt ſteps in, and by vertue of that authority he hath with his Father, he ſaith, he will <hi>declare the Decree:</hi> He procures a little ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of the devouring wrath of God, and undertakes to declare the Decree in the midſt of this wrathfull diſpenſation; now the Decree being onely concerning the matter of his Kingdome in the world, it's worthy our ſerious conſideration, whether it point at a time <hi>paſt,</hi> or the time <hi>preſent,</hi> or to <hi>come. PAST,</hi> I conceive it cannot be, for we doe not find that this Decree hath been declared in former times, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with the weighty and materiall circumſtances in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> Declared, as his right and Title to the Kingdomes and poſſeſſions of the Kings and Rulers of the earth; in oppoſition to the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of the world, though the beſt and moſt Saint-like of them, who <hi>Take CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NSELL againſt the Lord, and his anointed,</hi> that is, act againſt him hiddenly, that it appears not to the vulgar eye; and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly addreſt to the Kings and Rulers of the world, as matter for their conſideration; denouncing no leſſe than <hi>periſhing, death,</hi> to thoſe that yeeld not to him; pronouncing them <hi>bleſſed,</hi> who forſaking their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Lords and <hi>Rulers,</hi> put their truſt in him: Now no time paſt being able to ſhew this <hi>Decree</hi> thus declared, therefore it cannot point out to us that part of time.</item>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170601:6"/>
                  <item>3 Here is but a little time given men to repent in; which argues the day is far ſpent, and the night is at hand, the glaſſe is almoſt run out, there's but a few ſands behind to run; the voyce was all the day long, beſeeching and woeing to repentance, by loving and patheticall perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>We beſeech you,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>in Christs ſtead,</hi> ſetting before men the tenderneſſe of the heart of Chriſt to ſinners, and that match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe love of his that mov'd him to ſhed his blood for them; pourtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before them in a lively manner a crucified Chriſt, with his Crowne of Thornes on his head, his wounds in his hands and ſides, blood and water guſhing out, and all this (with the merits of his death and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings) to perſwade men to believe the willingneſſe of the heart of Chriſt to ſave ſinners, and that they would come and take him upon his owne tearmes, that they may be made happy by him. But now the day is ſo far ſpent, the evening come, and the time for repentance al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt expired, the voyce is altered, as we ſee in the laſt Verſe of the Pſalme, <hi>Kiſſe the Son leaſt he be angry,</hi> &amp;c. A haſty exhortation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſubmiſſion to Chriſt, from the conſideration of his anger; it's but a little time he will waite for you, if you come not in to him, when his wrath is kindled but a little, you will periſh from the way, then <hi>they</hi> will be onely bleſſed, that have put their truſt in him. This Text holds a faire correſpondencie with that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11, 12. <hi>He that is unjuſt, let him be unjuſt ſtill; and he which is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill: And he that is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill; and he that is holy, let him be holy ſtill. And behold I come quickly, and my reward is with me, to give every man according as his worke ſhall be.</hi> And that other followes at the back of it, <hi>Bring hither thoſe mine enemies that would not that I ſhould raigne over them, and ſlay them before me.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 We have cloſely coucht in this Pſalme, ſome ſignes of the coming of Chriſt, as <hi>The Apoſtacy and falling away of many</hi> (as appears by what followes) and the <hi>abounding of iniquity, upon which the love of many ſhall wax cold;</hi> for certainly, iniquity muſt very much abound, when ſuch perſons as theſe Rulers are (who they be, and what they are, will be made manifeſt by and by) ſhall take counſell together to break the bands of the Lord, and his anointed, and caſt their cords from them: Which manifeſts that the love they once made ſhew of, is very cold indeed.</item>
                  <item>5 Here's a time ſpoken of, wherein Chriſt ſhall deale with the Kings and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the earth, concerning the matters of his Kingdome, and provoke them to give place to him, <hi>whoſe right it is.</hi> All the day long, he had been dealing with men promiſcuouſly, but now he is taking to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170601:6"/>himſelfe his great power the father hath given him, he deales in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and more then ordinary manner, with the Kings and Rulers of the earth.</item>
                  <item>Laſtly, This Pſalme ſeems by the ſtile of it, to preſent to us Gods coming to judge the world; God coming downe to view the works of mens hands (as he did to <hi>Sodome,</hi> to ſee what men did there) and beholding the abominable wickedneſſes of men, he asks the reaſon of it, <hi>why it is ſo?</hi> and finding none to give an account, no Advocate to plead their cauſe, (his Son not appearing for them) he breaks forth into wrath and fury againſt the world, reſolves to delay no longer, but to execute the Decree, performe his Promiſe to his Son, and powre downe his judgements upon the world: Sitting on his Throne, he <hi>laughs at them, hath them in deriſion, ſpeaks to them in wrath, and vexes them in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Whoſoever doth ſeriouſly ponder and weigh theſe Reaſons, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive will ſee cauſe to believe it for a Truth, That this Propheſie takes in all that ſpace of time between Chriſts firſt and ſecond coming.</p>
               <p>But in the ſecond place, There is ſome ſpeciall particle of time, pointed out unto us by that ſignificant <hi>THEN</hi> in the fifth verſe: <hi>THEN ſhall he ſpeake unto them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure. THEN,</hi> when? The holy Ghoſt affords us by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Aſpect of this <hi>THEN,</hi> many Characters to guide us into a competent knowledge of that diſmall time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THEN,</hi> may have reſpect unto the heatheniſh rage, and vaine imaginations of the firſt company of enemies; and it ſignifies thus much, that when the rage of the one, and folly of the other came to the full, <hi>THEN</hi> God would judge them; and truly, at that time God put the old Dragon to his ſhifts, he had been quite extinct, and put beſide his Kingdome, had he not evaded it, by giving his power to the Beaſt (Antichriſt) and being contented to raigne by his ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, the man of ſin; but in a ſpeciall and peculiar manner this remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable <hi>THEN,</hi> hath reſpect unto the laſt of thoſe counterfeits, that would be eſteemed Gods Deputies, yet are in truth Satans Inſtruments, againſt the Lord and his anointed. So that,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p n="1">1 <hi>THEN when the R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LERS take counſell together. R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LERS,</hi> men that are neither of the number of the Heathen, nor of the Kings of the earth, but a more refined ſort of men; ſuch, as would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Judges as at the firſt, and counſellours as at the beginning. R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LERS,</hi> not of the earth, no, that is not expreſt, onely there are Kings of the earth; but theſe counſellors are <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LERS;</hi> of what?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170601:7"/>ſurely it's but genuine to ſay, they would be accounted <hi>Rulers</hi> of the Lords people: But Chriſt when he comes to deale with them in the tenth verſe, ſaith, they are of the earth as well as the Kings, <hi>Judges of the EARTH:</hi> He diſcovers their hidden works of darkneſſe, and makes them appear in their true colours; Thus much I conceive is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to us by this, that though when Chriſt comes to ſpeak to them, he calls them, as indeed they are, <hi>Judges of the earth;</hi> yet here they are termed onely <hi>Rulers,</hi> (and that in oppoſition to the Kings of the earth) that is, ſuch as they termed themſelves, and would be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LERS, Counſellors:</hi> No Heatheniſh Emperors, nor Popiſh Kings, but <hi>refined Rulers;</hi> here's Satan transformed into an Angel of light; The Heathens cannot prevaile, and the Kings of the earth doe not proſper, thus Satan being put to his laſt ſhift, turnes Saint in ſhew, ſets up his Rulers, that have neither the violent rage of the Heathen, nor the open prophaneſſe of the Kings, but the ſoft hand of profeſſion, to become nurſing fathers, and nurſing mothers to the Church of Chriſt, (as appears by what followes) even while they are taking counſell together againſt the Lord and his anointed: For,</p>
               <p>They are <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LERS,</hi> that having cut off ſome of the Kings of the earth, <hi>Rule</hi> in their ſtead: which is neceſſarily imply'd in the Text, for we know that the Kings of the earth (thoſe that committed fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Beaſt, and gave their power to her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2.17.) ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led over the whole world (that part which is called the Chriſtian world, in which this conteſt is, betweene Chriſt and his enemies) yet at laſt ſteps up ſome <hi>Rulers,</hi> and they get Dominion among the Kings; for it's clear by the Order of the words in the Text, theſe <hi>Rule,</hi> and take <hi>counſell,</hi> while the reſt of the Kings are <hi>ſetting themſelves</hi> againſt the Lord and his anointed: which could not be, if theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> had not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed ſome of the Kings, ruling in their ſtead; otherwiſe, there would be no place for them, the Kings of the earth having all the Chriſtian world under their Dominion, it's no way reaſonable to conceive, that thoſe who love their Crownes ſo well, would willingly give their glory to others.</p>
               <p>And why may we not ſay, that theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> get their Dominion by fighting the Lambs battels againſt the Beaſt; for, <hi>A Kingdome divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand;</hi> If Satan be againſt Satan, how can he proſper? Therefore it's not reaſonable to think, that Satan ſhould ſet them on work to deſtroy <hi>his Kings,</hi> but that theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> did fight up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Chriſt, and his people.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170601:7"/>
               <p>Againe, Satan is on the looſing hand by theſe <hi>Rulers,</hi> for, as Satan was not ſo viſible nor ſo abſolute in his rule over the world, in the Beaſts time, as in the Dragons; ſo now he looſes more ground in the loſſe of his Kings, then when he loſt his Dragon; and can it be thought the wiſe Serpent would doe himſelfe this miſchief? Further, if theſe had gone out to warre upon any lower account, they would have been Kings ſtill; as we ſee dayly, when one King is gone, another gets up into his ſeat, yet but a King; certainly, it's ſome weighty reaſon, that moves them to forſake the glorious Title of a King, and make ſuch refined pretenſions, as the very name <hi>Ruler</hi> (conſidering it ſtands in the Text in oppoſition to the preceding Heathens and Kings) ſignifies to us they will be forc't to.</p>
               <p>Againe, They are <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LERS,</hi> that have given profeſt ſubjection to the Scepter of Chriſt: That is hinted to us in the third verſe, <hi>Let us breake their bands aſunder:</hi> That theſe bands can be no other but that part of the yoke of Chriſt to which they have ſubmitted, thoſe Lawes and Commands of Chriſt to which they have ſubjected them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, being convinced in their conſciences it was their duty ſo to doe: is clear to me upon theſe grounds.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Otherwiſe the holy Ghoſt ſhould commit Tautology, and unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary redundancy of ſpeech; for Interpreters (and that according to the truth) expound theſe <hi>bands</hi> and <hi>cords,</hi> mention'd in the Text, to be no other then the Lawes and Commands of Chriſt: And would it not be a derogating from the glory of this bleſſed word of God, and that excellent ſignificancy that is in every tittle of it, to ſay, that theſe two manner of expreſſions, ſignifie but one and the ſame thing, to give to it no more than a bare elegancy of ſpeech? Surely then, one part of the verſe would be ſuperfluous, and may be left out, which God forbid: This were to charge the word of God, and ſo God himſelfe, with that imperfection vaine man is ſubject to; which I preſume none that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes himſelfe a Chriſtian dares to doe. And if this be granted (which cannot be denyed) that there is a weighty ſignificancy in both parts of the verſe; then</p>
               <p n="2">2 What more genuine Interpretation can be given? For how come the Lawes of Chriſt to be <hi>bands</hi> to a man, but by his being actually bound with them? As the cords and withes wherewith <hi>Sampſon</hi> was bound, were not his <hi>bands</hi> before he became bound with them; they were cords and withes before, but then they were his <hi>bands,</hi> which he brake in ſunder: They cannot be called a mans <hi>bands</hi> in reſpect of the duty that lyes upon him to yield obedience to them, for ſo they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170601:8"/>
                  <hi>cords,</hi> which theſe men endeavour to caſt away from them. A man becomes bound, either by <hi>Covenant, Oath, Vow,</hi> or <hi>Engagement;</hi> when a man ſhall make a Covenant to walk in obedience to ſuch and ſuch Lawes, and bind himſelfe to the performance of it with an Oath; when he ſhall make a Vow, and engage to doe ſuch and ſuch things; though theſe duties and obligations were but <hi>cords</hi> before, yet now by theſe tyes upon him, they are become his <hi>bands;</hi> theſe <hi>Rulers,</hi> being thus ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bound, take counſell together <hi>to breake theſe bands aſunder, and to caſt away the cords from them,</hi> that they are not as yet bound with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If it be objected, <hi>That in the Text it's ſaid,</hi> Their bands, <hi>that is, the bands of the Lord and his anointed, ſo that they cannot be the bands of the Rulers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 It's brought in as the ſpeech of the <hi>Rulers,</hi> and ſo I conceive holds forth unto us their Apoſtacy, who now in an opprobrious ſcorn, call them their <hi>bands,</hi> thereby denying that they were at all obliged to the obſervance of them: Or</item>
                  <item>2 By this terme, <hi>their bands,</hi> may be intimated to us thoſe Lawes of Chriſt, which Chriſt by the common and ordinary workings of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, had wrought in theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> ſome kind of love to, which moved them to a ſubjection to them; or, by his providence had neceſſitated them ſo to doe, otherwiſe they ſaw they could not proſper in their work; or, that the people of God, Chriſts anointed, by their exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, calling upon them, and that formidable aſſiſtance they gave unto them while they ſtood for Chriſt againſt Satan in his Kings, had obliged them to be bound with; ſo that theſe may be truly called <hi>their bands,</hi> becauſe they are the <hi>cords,</hi> with which the Lord and his anointed have bound them; of which they cannot be freed, except they break them: yet ſtill they are the <hi>Rulers bands,</hi> which they take counſell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to break. Therefore</item>
                  <item>3 The conſideration of the different carriage of theſe <hi>Rulers,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>bands</hi> and the <hi>cords,</hi> will add ſome further ſatisfaction; they will <hi>breake their bands, and caſt away their cords;</hi> if the <hi>bands</hi> had no more tye upon them than the <hi>cords,</hi> the ſame ſlight manner of carriage of theirs towards the <hi>cords,</hi> would ſerve them alſo to be rid of the <hi>bands:</hi> But it's far otherwiſe, though they think a bare caſting and putting away, will clear them of the <hi>cords;</hi> yet, they are ſenſible, the <hi>bands</hi> cleave ſo cloſe to them, they cannot be rid of them, unleſſe they break them; as <hi>Sampſon</hi> could not be free from his <hi>cords</hi> and withes,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170601:8"/>wherewith he was bound untill he had broken them: If they had not ſo obliged themſelves to the Lawes of Chriſt, as that they were bound by them, what need they take counſell to break them; a man needs not ſtand to break a <hi>cord</hi> to clear himſelfe of it, except he be bound therewith; if onely a proffer be made to bind him with it, he may put it by, and caſt it from him, that is eaſier for him ſo to doe, and will ſerve the turne, as here in the Text they conſult to doe; but if he be once bound with it, nothing but a forcible breaking of it will free him: So that this carriage of theirs, towards the <hi>bands</hi> and the <hi>cords,</hi> confirms our Aſſertion.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding this their profeſſed ſubjection to Chriſt, theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> turne Apoſtates; Satan debauches them, then entring into them, makes them his owne, to finiſh his warfare, to fight for him, though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another manner, in a more ſubtill method then formerly, bringing forth the very maſterpiece of Satans wiſedome, for we ſee here, they take <hi>Counſell together, againſt the Lord and his anointed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 THEN, when <hi>the Rulers take CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCELL: Counſell,</hi> in diſtinction from, and oppoſition to, the mad rage of the Heathen, and the open and publick boldneſſe of the Kings; theſe two kinds of vaſſals not thriving in their way, Satan runs to his Saintlike <hi>Rulers,</hi> as to a ſure refuge, his <hi>Counſellors;</hi> and they take <hi>counſell,</hi> a ſecret clandeſtin way, as expert Warriours, when great ſhot will not doe, againſt the wall of a City, or Fort, then they ſecretly undermine it, ſuppoſing to prevaile that way: a ſecret way, They will not ſcruple to tranſgreſſe the regular punctillio's of the Law in any caſe, but, from counſell to action pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, before their counſells may be knowne: Theſe <hi>take counſell,</hi> which way is beſt to be taken, what the moſt wiſe and prudent courſe may be, to accompliſh their deſigne by; if by any way, by any means or courſe whatſoever, they can have their will, and ſtabliſh themſelves, though it be never ſo wicked and unworthy. If no other way will ſerve, they will become Saints of the higheſt form: in ſhew, <hi>Pauls</hi> brethren, <hi>become all things to all men, that they may gaine ſome,</hi> for, they take <hi>counſell;</hi> and if need be (keeping a ſuitable decorum) ſpeak and act againſt all thoſe, though never ſo excellent in their Generation, that ſtand in the way of their deſignments.</p>
               <p>To find out ſome new and neat way, the ſteps of their Predeceſſors they will not exactly follow; no, they have ſeen the folly and weaknes of thoſe: But they ſeek after a curious piece of Art, whereby they may be able to doe that which all the world before them (their great grand-fathers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170601:9"/>the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and their fore-fathers the <hi>prophane Kings</hi> of the earth) could not doe, againſt the Lord and his anointed: They <hi>take counſell,</hi> they have wiſedome (though from below) with them; for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Where there's counſell there's wiſedome:</hi> They are the wiſeſt and moſt ſubtill inſtruments ever Satan made uſe of; they are <hi>Counſellors,</hi> ſuch as God who is wiſedome it ſelfe, thinks it high time for him to ariſe and diſappoint them, leaſt they prevaile againſt his beloved.</p>
               <p n="3">3 THEN, when <hi>the Rulers take Counſell TOGETHER;</hi> when there is a Combination and Confederacy in Counſells between theſe refined <hi>Rulers</hi> againſt the Lord and his anointed: when they ſhall combine together to make their hands ſtrong, that they may keep their Dominion, maugre all the oppoſition, the Lord and his holy ones make.</p>
               <p n="4">4 THEN, when <hi>the Rulers take counſell together AGAINST THE LORD AND HIS ANOINTED;</hi> that is Chriſt and his followers, his anointed ones with the unction of the ſpirit, that follow him in all his out-goings, againſt the backſlidings and Apoſtacies of theſe <hi>Rulers:</hi> True, the Apoſtles and Brethren in the fourth of the <hi>Acts,</hi> expound this of the father, and Chriſt the Son, that the father was this Lord, and Chriſt the anointed of his father; this they ſpake of the gathering together of the Heathen and <hi>Jewes</hi> againſt Chriſt, when they put him to death; but the father having <hi>given all power into his Sons hands, hath made him both Lord and Chriſt,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36. The father in recompence for his finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which he gave him to doe, hath made him Lord, and anointed him above his fellowes; and he aſcending up on high, gave his gifts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sons of men, anointing them according to his promiſe, with the unction of the ſpirit; and let the Prophet <hi>David</hi> expound his owne meaning, ſaith he in another place, <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord, ſit thou on my right hand</hi> (which Chriſt applies to himſelfe) ſo that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> underſtood Chriſt to be Lord. Againe, <hi>Touch not mine anointed, and doe my Prophets no harme;</hi> the <hi>anointed</hi> are his <hi>Prophets,</hi> and his <hi>Prophets</hi> are his anointed, and who theſe Prophets are, we may ſee in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> they are the Members of the Church of Chriſt; ſo that <hi>David</hi> Expounds his owne meaning, and clearly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelfe, to point out Chriſt and his anointed, in theſe words. Now the reaſon why I terme them the followers of Chriſt in ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall deſigne, is, becauſe if all the Lords Prophets be anointed, then
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170601:9"/>much more thoſe, (they have a greater meaſure of the anointing,) who follow the Lamb in his ſometimes rough, uncouth wayes of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, who keep cloſe to him when he is doing his ſtrange work, and bringing to paſſe his ſtrange act in the world, when he comes to take the Kingdomes of this world unto himſelfe, <hi>whoſe right it is to raigne:</hi> And they are with him againſt theſe <hi>Rulers,</hi> is ſtrongly imply'd, in that theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> are ſo cloſe in conſultation, and ſo fully bent againſt them; for, we cannot conceive, that theſe wiſe men would irritate any againſt them without a cauſe, but on the other hand, they wil foſter all that will come under their wing, and take protection from them; and truly, it's not a ſmall portion of this anointing will deliver them from the intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glements of theſe <hi>Rulers;</hi> for they are Saints as to us (or at leaſt to thoſe who have not a very narrow and quick inſpection into the ſtate of the times) the faireſt outſide ever Satan had; And without doubt many of the people of the Lord may be taken and deceived with them: Some good thing they will doe (or they'le prove but fooliſh Counſellors) they will goe as far to meet a diſſenting Brother, as it's poſſible for them, and not endanger their Dominion. If Satan cannot uphold his Dragon, he will be content with his Beaſt; but if he cannot keep up his Beaſt in any place, he will be ſatisfied with his Image; yea, rather than give out, the bare number of his name ſhall pleaſe him: So that many precious ſoules may be deluded for a time, if they take not great heed, otherwiſe that voyce would be needleſſe, <hi>Come out of her my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, leaſt ye be partakers of her ſins, and ſo of her plagues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 THEN, when they <hi>Take counſell together, to BREAK THEIR BANDS AS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDER, AND TO CAST AWAY THEIR CORDS FROM THEM.</hi> The conteſt goes high, by this time it's come to particulars: Before, it was but in generalls; and it's about no ſmall or triviall buſineſſe, but who ſhall have the Authority and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; The diſpute is about the Kingdome (that is clear from the whole Pſalme; ſaith God, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion:</hi> And the Decree is wholly concerning Chriſts Kingdome over the world) about the Authority and Legiſlative power; Chriſt and his anointed ſay, the father hath given them authority <hi>to bind Kings with chaines, and Nobles with fetters of iron;</hi> to bind the Rulers with his Lawes, as with a cord; and theſe Rulers <hi>take counſell together to break their bands aſunder, and caſt their cords from them.</hi> We have already given our ſence what theſe bands are.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Rulers take counſell to BREAK THEM AS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDER.</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170601:10"/>ſurely they had need of a greater than <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength, that would break the <hi>bands</hi> of God aſunder; but theſe think to doe it by ſlights and wiles, they <hi>take counſell:</hi> They would <hi>breake their bands,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be bound by the ſtrongeſt Oathes and Obligations, the largeſt Vowes and Declarations, the greateſt proteſtations and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet they muſt be broken rather than the Lord and his anointed ſhall have their due, and their right.</p>
               <p>And to <hi>CAST AWAY THEIR CORDS;</hi> what though theſe <hi>cords</hi> be the moſt righteous, holy and wholeſome Lawes of the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> (that will bleſſe thoſe with the greateſt happineſſe, that live in unfeigned obedience to them) that the Lord and his anointed would impoſe on them for their owne good and ſalvation; they will none of them, but take counſell to caſt them away, ſcorning and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them as a burden too heavy for man to bear, a yoke not fit for the neck of ſuch a free Creature as man is: <hi>Breake their bands, and caſt away their cords,</hi> that they may have no power over them, that they may be their ſubjects, and not their Lords, that they may not intrench upon their Dominion, nor deprive them of their worldly enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p n="6">6 THEN, when they <hi>TAKE CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCELL:</hi> Before they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to act; when upon conſultation they are ready to goe forth in all their might, crying, <hi>LET <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S breake their bands,</hi> &amp;c. Then God will ariſe and ſhew himſelfe, he will not ſuffer them to act their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels leaſt they prevaile, but while they are in <hi>counſell,</hi> he will take them to task, and let them find he can in wrath tumble them into thoſe pits and ſnares they have digged for others.</p>
               <p n="7">7 THEN, when the <hi>Kings of the earth ſet themſelves, and the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers take counſell together againſt the Lord and his anointed.</hi> The order of the words, in that the Holy Ghoſt brings in the Kings <hi>ſetting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> and the Rulers taking <hi>counſell together,</hi> before he tells us againſt whom; ſeems to me to be of ſufficient force to perſwade us, that here is a hint given us by the Holy Ghoſt, of another confederacy, that there ſhall be ſome agreement between the (remaining) Kings of the earth (or at leaſt ſome of them) and theſe <hi>Rulers, againſt the Lord and his anointed;</hi> and then will God ariſe, bear with them no longer, but <hi>ſpeak to them in his wrath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, THEN, when their Counſells ſhall be guilty of ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Apoſtacy, as moves God to <hi>laugh at them;</hi> when they ſet at naught the counſell and reproof of God (which ſurely is contain'd in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170601:10"/>thoſe bands and cords they reject) then, will God deale with them in that dreadfull manner mentioned, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24—<hi>ult. Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: But ye have ſet at nought all my counſell, and would none of my reproof, I alſo will laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your feare cometh. When your feare cometh as deſolation, and your deſtruction co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth as a whirlewind; when diſtreſſe and anguiſh cometh upon you; Then ſhall they call upon me, but I will not anſwer; they ſhall ſeeke me early, but they ſhall not find me: For that they hated knowledge, and did not chuſe the feare of the Lord; they would none of my counſell, they deſpiſed all my reproofe. Therefore ſhall they eate of the fruit of their owne way, and be filled with their owne deviſes; for the turning away of the ſimple ſhall ſlay them, and the proſperity of fooles ſhall deſtroy them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when the abomination of their counſells come to that height, that God ſhall <hi>have them in deriſion,</hi> which is ſomewhat more then <hi>to laugh;</hi> It may poſſibly be, that a man may <hi>laugh</hi> at one (and that in anger too) whom he yet loves; but to <hi>laugh with deriſion,</hi> argues perfect hatred: When their counſells and doings againſt the Lord, thus provoke the eyes of his glory, <hi>THEN, ſhall be ſpeake to them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if we would know when God will thus <hi>laugh at them, and have them in deriſion;</hi> The anſwer is plaine in the Text, he will doe it, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their taking counſel to break their bands aſunder, and to caſt away their cords from them: when the cry is, <hi>Let us breake their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords from us: He that ſitteth in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſhall laugh; the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee what a multitude of plaine Characters the Holy Ghoſt hath given of that time wherein God will come upon the world, and doe ſuch great things for his Son (who he hath made Lord, and ſet at his right hand) and his anointed ones: When we ſee theſe Characters written on the foreheads of the high ones of the earth, then we may ſafely ſay without haeſitation, That God will ſuddenly come in wrath and fury, take their Dominion away, and give it to that rejected cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone, <hi>whoſe right it is to raigne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Let us now make a ſtand, and by a ſerious review, ſee what may be obſerved as a beneficiall Leſſon for us to learne.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That in theſe latter diſpenſations, men may fill up <hi>the meaſure of their iniquity,</hi> and bring judgement upon their Generation, <hi>by a bare ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king counſell againſt the Lord and his anointed.</hi> When the Rulers <hi>take
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170601:11"/>counſell together,</hi> then, God will <hi>ſpeake unto them in wrath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 How <hi>Great matter of Comfort</hi> is it to the people of God, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Lamb, that their father is ſo far from ſuffering their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to prevaile againſt them in theſe laſt dayes, that <hi>All that ever they can doe cannot prevaile to breake one band aſunder,</hi> (that is, ſo, as to free themſelves from it, to ſettle themſelves upon another foundation) <hi>but while they are taking counſell together, God comes and gives them the rout,</hi> let's them heare his mighty voyce in wrath, that they run to the holes of the rock, and cry to the mountaines and to the hills to hide them from the tempeſt of his fury: He will take the crafty in their owne ſnares, though they take counſell to draw the Lords people into their ſnares, and to throw them into the pits they have digged; yet, ſhall they not be able to bring it to paſſe, but they themſelves ſhall be taken with, and fall into them; then the ſcourge ſhall teach them <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar's</hi> leſſon, <hi>That the moſt high rules in the Kingdomes of men:</hi> In former times, his long-ſufferance was much, he lets them goe on to rage and madneſſe, to open and bold (yea, and prevalent) act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſetting themſelves againſt them; but now, his patience will waite no longer, he will deale with them, before they are well warme in their counſells; <hi>He will cut the worke ſhort in righteouſneſſe, becauſe a ſhort worke will the Lord make upon the earth; thoſe dayes ſhall be ſhortned for the Elect's ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 What <hi>a darke and diſtracting day, is this day?</hi> When ſuch men as theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> have appear'd to be, having followed the Lamb ſo far, to the cutting off ſome of the Kings of the earth, and proclaiming the Lord to be King, made his <hi>cords</hi> (his Lawes) to become their <hi>bands,</hi> binding themſelves with them (as hath been open'd at large) when ſuch men ſhall now turne head, and deale ſubtilly with the Lord and his anointed, taking counſell againſt them: What a <hi>darke day of Apoſtacy is this day?</hi> The Dragon is able to caſt downe a third part of the Stars to the earth; and when the Stars fall from heaven, what bitterneſſe will betide the Children of men? Without queſtion theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> by their malevolent influence, will throw downe many who have been as ſhining lights, to the loſſe of their glorious profeſſion.</p>
               <p>How great will be the <hi>diſtracting darkneſſe of this day?</hi> When the cunning of theſe <hi>Counſellors</hi> (working underboard) not ſhewing openly their intentions, ſhall amuſe men, that the moſt ſharp-ſighted obſerver, can ſcarcely diſcerne the temper of the times, ſo, as to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the truth of his obſervation to the underſtanding of others, (for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170601:11"/>we muſt remember that Satan now is at his laſt game, though men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to worſhip the Beaſt, and to receive his mark, yet if they keep but within the number of his name, he will eſteem them as his good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and be therewith content.) Here are Devils in the ſhape of Saints, carrying things in ſuch a poſture, as that almoſt all men are in a maze, not knowing what to dream the iſſue of things will be; ſurely, this day may truly be called <hi>neither day nor night,</hi> neither Satans night of darkneſſe, nor Gods day of light, in which men not having light enough to ſee clearly, nor wiſedome enough to light up their Candles, goe poreing in the dark, ready to ſtumble at every ſtraw of infirmity they meet with in the ſincere hearts of the times, in the mean while ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard a choaking, ſwallowing downe the Camels of State abominations; yet, notwithſtanding all this, God hath promiſed that <hi>at evening time it ſhall be light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What a <hi>diſtracting day of diviſion is this,</hi> among Gods own people? When ſome good ſoules exerciſing their charity ſhall conſider the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> former good actions, and plead them, with their apprehenſions of their preſent good intentions in what they doe, to thoſe, who being of a quicker inſight into the ſtate of buſineſſes, ſhall diſcover and aſſert their Apoſtacies, to perſwade them into a favourable conſtruction of their proceedings; and when on the other ſide, thoſe, who retaining their ſincerity in the life of it, being enlightened by the ſpirit of God in the <hi>worke of the day,</hi> both as to the work God would have done, and the counter-workings of the evill one, ſhall cry out amaine againſt thoſe abominations, that God may not be without witneſſe to the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of his honour, which men would lay in the duſt: what inward fends and heart-burnings? What breach of all Goſpel rules, will be the ſad fruit of this diſmall day? Let none ſay theſe things are far fetcht, and have no connexion with the Text, if men will ſeriouſly with unbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed judgements weight the ground-work, I conceive they cannot but ſee theſe things a neceſſary deduction from the premiſes.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The <hi>great faithfullneſſe and love of God</hi> to his Son Jeſus Chriſt his anointed one, that although out of his long-ſuffering he bore long with men, in their actings againſt his Son in the conteſt concerning his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Propheticall Office (though then at his appointed time he met with them to their confuſion) yet, when it comes to the matter of his Kingdome, which the father is ſo ſtrongly engaged to give him, and wherein his honour and glory is ſo abundantly concerned, <hi>THEN,</hi> will he waite no longer, but even while they are <hi>taking counſell,</hi> while
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170601:12"/>they are but thinking of it, while they are conſulting the wiſeſt and moſt feaſible way to bring to paſſe their purpoſes; it ſo enrages the eyes of his glory to behold it, that he will not ſuffer them to break ſo much as a piece of a <hi>band,</hi> but he will make bare his arme, and ſpeak to them in wrath, by the mighty working of his power; The Lord will <hi>breake the ſtaffe of the wicked, and the Scepter of the Rulers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 It's worthy our obſervation, That thoſe who <hi>bring up the reare of the enemies of the Lord and his anointed, are Counſellors.</hi> Or if you will thus, <hi>That the laſt</hi> (and ſo the moſt ſubtill refined) <hi>deſigne of Satan againſt the Lord and his anointed, is managed by A CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>N<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CILL. They take counſell together;</hi> ſuch, as having the example of all the feates of policy former times have brought forth, and the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of that patterne of prudence and wiſedome, the old ſubtill Serpent hath been drawing from the beginning of the world to this day, ſhall be ſo crafty and wylie, as that God by that ſhall be engaged to rouſe up himſelfe in his might, leaſt they prevaile; The <hi>Rulers</hi> of the world <hi>taking counſell,</hi> become wiſe againſt the Lord and his anointed; Their exceſſe in humane wiſedome and policy, engages God to ſhew forth the ſuper-excellency of his Divine wiſedome, being above them in that wherein they deale proudly.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Although the fins of theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> be not ſo groſly prophane as their predeceſſors, but their thred is of a finer ſpin; <hi>yet, they are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch aggravations as the Lord Jeſus cannot brooke:</hi> They provoke him (him who is the onely Mediator for ſinners) that he will not ſpeak one word to his father on their behalfe; Though God come with fury in his face, asking the reaſon of their doings, why is it ſo? and his wrath wax hot againſt them, we ſee our Lord Jeſus appears not, pleads not a ſillable for them, we read not a word of his interceſſion in this place: Formerly notwithſtanding their ſins were more groſſe, and far greater in themſelves, to the ſlaying the Lord of glory, he prayes, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgive them, for they know not, what they doe;</hi> and the Martyrs (as <hi>Stephen</hi> did) could beg on behalfe of their murderers, <hi>Lord lay not this ſin to their charge:</hi> But now men are become wiſe, knowing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners againſt his glory, <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> be hath not a word to ſpeak for them, all that he will doe is to declare the Decree <hi>[I will declare the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree]</hi> to the world and them, if they will hear, well, but if not, they ſhall feele his wrath, and <hi>periſh from the way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 That when the world and its <hi>Rulers</hi> come to this manner and meaſure of ſin, <hi>they are excluded the interceſſion of Chriſt,</hi> (he prayes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170601:12"/>not for them, neither is it the fathers mind he ſhould; when God puts him upon asking, it's not any thing for them, but their poſſeſſions and uſurpations for himſelfe, and a <hi>rod of iron</hi> to puniſh and deſtroy them) <hi>and ſo the prayers of the Saints.</hi> We ought not to pray for them, and for that, for whom and for which Chriſt prayed not; his interceſſion ought to be the patterne of our prayers; otherwiſe our petitions are not acceptable, for, <hi>in his beloved he accepts us.</hi> It hath been ſeverall times at this paſſe with the world, <hi>Pray not thou for this people, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lift up cry nor prayer for them, neither make interceſſion to me, for I will not hear thee.</hi> God loves not to hear his people make ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, he hath no mind to grant; <hi>Though Moſes and Samuel ſtood before me, yet my mind could not be towards this people; caſt them out of my ſight, and let them goe forth. Though theſe three men, Noah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, and Job were in it, they ſhould deliver but their owne ſoules by their righteouſneſſe, ſaith the Lord God.</hi> And now it's come into the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament againe; the world hath run its round, and is gotten into a like poſture it was in when a flood of wrath overwhelmed it: What a ſad condition is this world now in? It's tottering and there's none to underprop it; it's ſinking and there's none to uphold it; The wrath of God is hovering over it, ready to fall upon it, and there's none to plead, to undertake for it; Surely the world is beholding to the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Chriſt for its ſtanding, and now that ceaſes, the foundations thereof are out of courſe, and it's falling: The day of the Lord is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon it as a Theef in the night, <hi>wherein the Heavens ſhall flee away as a ſcrowle, the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, and the earth with the workes therein ſhall be burnt up.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The ſecond part of our work is, To ſearch into the <hi>worke to be done</hi> in this remarkable time: Here is the work of the father, and of the Son.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The work of the father, which is two-fold, <hi>A worke of wrath</hi> to his enemies; which is amplified by a double expreſſion, <hi>ſpeaking in wrath,</hi> and <hi>vexing them in his ſore diſpleaſure:</hi> And ſecondly, <hi>A work of love and faithfullneſſe</hi> to his Son.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then ſhall he ſpeake unto them in his wrath.</hi> God ſpeaks to men in divers manners, by the voyce of his <hi>providences,</hi> the voyce of his <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> the voyce of his <hi>rod,</hi> and the voyce of his <hi>judgements;</hi> and when God ſpeaks by all in wrath, his <hi>providences</hi> blinding their eyes, his <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> hardening their hearts, his <hi>rod</hi> driving them from him, and (as the fruit of the former) his <hi>judgements</hi> ceaſe upon them; here's a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170601:13"/>dreadfull day of wrath indeed, now God ſpeaks to them in wrath: But his hath ſpeciall relation to the voyce of his <hi>ward;</hi> for, what doth he peak to them in wrath? The Text tells us, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Syon;</hi> the Goſpel of the Kingdome: And that muſt needs be a day of wrath and terrors indeed, when that word which was wont to be a word of ſalvation, a word of love and good will, ſhall now be a word of wrath, in wrath. O ſad!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>God ſpeaks his word in wrath to a people.</p>
               <p n="1">1 When it hath contrary effects upon them; <hi>a ſavour of death unto death,</hi> inſtead of a ſavour of life unto life: As in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11, 12. This Evangelicall Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> muſt <hi>make the hearts of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fat, their eares heavy, and ſhut their eyes;</hi> and that by ſpeaking ſuch gracious words unto them as he doth throughout his whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie: Certainly, this is none other but the wrath of God upon a <hi>wanton and backſliding people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 When God layes ſtumbling-blocks before a people, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not nor hearken to the word, but ſtumble and fall upon it, and periſh, according to that in <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.21. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, behold, I will lay ſtumbling-blocks before this people, and the fathers and the ſons together ſhall fall upon them: The neighbour and his friend ſhall periſh.</hi> This alſo is none other but the wrath of God upon <hi>a ſtubborne rebellious people:</hi> They had ſaid they <hi>would not heare,</hi> and ſaith God let it be ſo, <hi>they ſhall not heare;</hi> he throwes ſtumbling-blocks in their way, leaſt they ſhould follow the voyce of his word, and he ſhould bleſſe them: Yet theſe ſtumbling-blocks are not ſuch, as in the leaſt extenuate or leſſen their iniquity, by giving them good and right ground to plead a neceſſity for their doings, but ſuch, as men make to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: True, God layes ſtumbling-blocks before them, yet it's them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that make thoſe ſo to them; they are not ſo to a ſanctified heart, (he, by the wing of faith can fly over them) but to an earthy lump of clay, whoſe eye is fixed upon no higher than a carnall and worldly glory: As</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Gods making uſe of obſcure mean fooliſh inſtruments (in the worlds eye) to publiſh his word and Decree to the world: He hath choſen <hi>the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, the weake to confound thoſe which are mighty, and the baſe and deſpiſed things of the world, and things that are not, to bring to nought things that are, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence.</hi> This hath been his courſe all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long ſince the world began, none muſt deliver his people from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170601:13"/>famine, but a deſpiſed <hi>Joſeph;</hi> The Meſſage of rebuke and threatning judgement to a Prince in <hi>Iſrael</hi> (good old <hi>Ely</hi>) muſt be ſent by <hi>Samuel</hi> a weak Child, unskilfull in the word of Propheſie: And as if none of the Princes and Royall blood could be moulded after Gods owne heart, he muſt take <hi>David</hi> from the ſheepfold, and make him (a mean ſhepheard) Governour over and a deliverer of his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen people; And who are his Heralds to proclaime the Goſpel of the Kingdome, but a company of poore deſpicable Fiſhermen? He leaves the wiſe and learned Rabbies, Scribes, and holy Phariſees of the times, and chooſeth the fooles of the world, makes them prevalent to pull downe Principalities, powers, and ſtrong holds, and they ſhall one day prevaile to the trampling their enemies under their feet as the mire in the ſtreets. Thus, out of the mouths of Babes and ſucklings, he ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrength, perfecting his praiſe, the ſpirituall man can diſcerne the glory of it, his heart will admire and adore it; But the men of this world, they take offence, ſtumble and fall to the periſhing of their ſoules: What! will God forſake our wiſe and holy men, that excell in moſt excellent virtues, and ſpeak by ſuch Idiots, raſh fooles, vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bablers, and mad men as they are? No, they cannot, they will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it: If <hi>Peter</hi> and his brethren be filled with the holy Ghoſt, they are <hi>drunken:</hi> If <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak of the true God, he is a <hi>vaine-babler:</hi> and reaſon of Temperance and Judgement to come, <hi>much learning hath made him mad;</hi> This is the ſence and judgement of the world.</item>
                  <item>2 The infirmities of his Meſſengers; their not walking up fully to their profeſſion of the glorious Goſpel, nor ſo exactly as they ought by the line of the word of truth in their mouth: Now, the men of this world drawing the line of their judgement from a wrong point, they think thoſe mens Principles nought, and hypocrittically rotten, the word of truth in their mouth an errour, a deluſion, a lye, not remembring the beſt of men muſt have their graines of allowance: Here, they take offence, ſtumble, and fall, riſing up with their backs towards the truth: This God permits in judgement and wrath to the world, that they <hi>may ſtumble, and fall, and periſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 The manner of delivering the word of truth in this day of wrath, is a great ſtumbling-block to the world: <hi>God ſpeaks to them in wrath,</hi> he was wont to ſpeak in love, the Goſpel was glad Tidings; but now the word, is a word of wrath, threatning judgement and deſtruction to the world for their wicked Apoſtacies and rebellions againſt the Lord and his anointed; O ſay they, this is no Goſpel ſpirit, but a ſpirit of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170601:14"/>deluſion; although, it's but the ſame Dialect the Holy Ghoſt uſeth throughout the <hi>Revelation</hi> againſt ſpiritual <hi>Babylon</hi> (Antichriſt:) At this they ſtumble, and caſt the word of life far from them, thinking they have good ground ſo to doe.</item>
                  <item>4 The Apoſtacy of falſe Brethren from the truth; this is a great ſtumbling-block to the world, by this the world blindly judgeth, that the way of the truth is but a meer phanſie, and hath not that real good in it the world hath, otherwiſe theſe men would not change their ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they cannot think they would take worſe for better, thus they ſtumble, and fall, and periſh: This is alſo the judgement of God upon the world.</item>
                  <item>5 The ſpirituality of the truth; At this alſo the men of the world ſtumble, being blind and not apprehending the truth aright, put ſtrange gloſſes upon it, and draw unworthy and uncouth concluſions from it, repreſenting it (Satan helping them) to themſelves and others in a monſtrous ſhape, at which they ſtumble, and fall, and periſh: As thoſe men did, <hi>John</hi> 6. when Chriſt had been treating of that great and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Myſtery, of union with him, it is ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 66. <hi>From that time many of his Diſciples went back, and walked no more with him.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>And vex them</hi> (or <hi>trouble them,</hi> as it is in the margent) <hi>in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi> When God ſpeaks in wrath, ſurely it cannot but bring great trouble to men: When God ſpake in wrath to <hi>Saul,</hi> that he had rejected him, and given the Kingdome to a neighbour of his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then he, how did it vex and trouble his ſoule? What feare ceized on him? How did it torment him, when he perceived the Lord being departed from him was with <hi>David?</hi> Oh, ſaith he to his Son, <hi>Thou Son of a perverſe woman, doe I not know thou haſt choſen the Son of Jeſſe to thine owne confuſion, for as long as the Son of Jeſſe liveth upon the ground, thou ſhalt not be eſtabliſhed, nor thy Kingdome.</hi> How was that moſt excellent King <hi>Solomon troubled,</hi> when God ſpake in wrath, that he had given the greateſt part of his Kingdome to another? And what <hi>trouble</hi> and vexation of ſpirit did it bring to all the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when at any time God ſpake unto them in his wrath, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the matters of their Kingdome? The whole Hiſtory of the Kings make it evident.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi> That muſt needs be a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and terrible trouble, great anxiety of ſpirit, that comes from the ſore diſpleaſure of the great God: If we can imagine any trouble and vexation to be greater and more deadly then another, that muſt needs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170601:14"/>be it: <hi>Vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure;</hi> O dreadfull! what horrors! what gaſtly terrours of death, will encompaſſe men about in that day? If they turne to the left hand; to their Ciſternes they have hewne out to themſelves, behold, they are broken, and hold no water; If to the props they thought to have upheld themſelves with, behold, they are rotten, and will not bear them up; and if to the arm of fleſh, the ſtrength of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> they truſted to, behold, it's a broken reed, and pierceth their hands: If to the right hand, from whence they are fallen; behold, nothing but the frowning brow of a wrathfull God, and the fiery ſpirit of an enraged people; whoſe heart burneth with the zeale of God, for the honour and glory of their God: What killing diſappointments are here? What no hope? Alas, alas, very little, or none at all: What is the (feared) fruit this brings forth? Why, they repent not, but blaſpheme the God of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But what is this that God ſpeaks to them that thus troubles them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Anſwer you will find in the Text, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion;</hi> It's the word of the Kingdome; that God will take their Crownes from off their heads, and ſet them on the head of Chriſt: How was <hi>Herod</hi> troubled, and all <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with him, when he heard but a <hi>where is he that is borne King of the Jewes?</hi> How greatly did the tidings of a rightfull King trouble him? His conſcience flyes in his face, and ſtings him, his jealouſie and feare of looſing what he had ſurreptitiouſly gotten, rent his heart with a thouſand anxieties, which vented themſelves in unheard of cruelties againſt poore Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents: And the Stories of the Martyrs tell us, that ſome Emperors af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of <hi>Herod,</hi> have been ſo troubled with the fear of, (and jealous of) King Jeſus his robbing them of their Thrones, they have ſought the deſtruction of the whole lineage of <hi>David:</hi> And at this day, what a dreadfull troubleſome ſtory is it to the Kings and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the earth, to heare the doctrine of the Kingdome of Chriſt is aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and preached to the people? How jealous and full of wrath are they! How doth it trouble them!</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why ſhould men be troubled and vexed at this word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truly there's ſome reaſon why the men of the world ſhould be troubled.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Becauſe the word is ſpoken, as that which God hath already done; <hi>I HAVE ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion:</hi> I have done it, ſaith God, and the ſubſequent is eaſily drawne; you muſt ſubmit to him, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170601:15"/>you periſh: If the doctrine were this, That Chriſt ſhould have a Kingdome many hundred yeares to come, the people of God might preach it while their lungs laſted, and meet with no oppoſition from the men of the world, let them alone till that day, think they; but when the word comes ſo neere them, as to ſay, now is the time, God hath already done it, the time of performance is come; This galls them, rubs on the ſore too hard, and troubles them.</item>
                  <item>2 Becauſe this Doctrine is preacht in oppoſition to them: <hi>YET have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion: YET,</hi> though you have taken counſell againſt the Lord and his anointed, to <hi>break their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords;</hi> to keep them at a low and under rate, as <hi>Pharoah</hi> did, that they may be your ſubjects and ſervants, and never be able to become your Lords: Yet ſaith God, I will ſpeak to you in wrath, and trouble you with this, <hi>I have ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion:</hi> I will doe it, you ſhall know and find that I am above you in that wherein you are ſo ſubtilly wiſe; in ſpite of you he ſhall be King, and raigne, it's his right, and he ſhall have it; I have promiſed him, and I will give the Kingdome to him, maugre all your envy and malice; I would not ſuffer the Heathen to keep the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from him; and have brought downe to the duſt thoſe Kings of the earth you have ſlaine, for their attempts againſt him; and ſhall you proſper in your Apoſtacies and rebellions againſt him? I would not bear with their ſuperſtition, and ſhall I now connive at your hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſies? Shall I ſuffer and permit you to keep the Kingdome from him, and to interrupt the performance of my Promiſes? No: know, I ſpeak it to you in my wrath, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 Becauſe it will deſtroy all their Idols, deprive them of all their dear enjoyments; their powers, with their pomp and glory, to which their heart cleaves ſo cloſe, this ſword of Chriſts mouth will ſmite them all; their Idols of gold, and their Idols of ſilver, and their Idols of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all theſe will it conſume: And their Kingdomes muſt become the Kg domes of the Lords Chriſt, and all their Dominion, and the greatneſſe (the glory of it) ſhall be given to the Saints of the moſt high, thoſe whom they have trampled upon, and to whom they have been ſo barbarouſly ungratefull: Theſe things <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>vex</hi> theſe <hi>Rulers,</hi> that they gnaw their tongues for anguiſh and paine.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And ſurely this is a day of great wrath indeed; as when two Kings, and both ſtrong, are ſtriving for a Crowne, it's likely to be a day of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170601:15"/>great wrath, a bloody day: So, this day, for behold, what a feaſt will God make on this day, <hi>For the Fowles that flye in the midſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the fleſh of Kings, the fleſh of Captaines and mighty men, the fleſh of Horſes, and of them that ſit on them, the fleſh of all men, both free and bond, both ſmall and great.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>We may conclude from theſe things:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 It's not <hi>unſuitable to a Goſpel ſpirit,</hi> to denounce the wrath of God againſt <hi>Rulers,</hi> for their Apoſtacies and abhominable hypocriſies; yea, and to deale particularly with them, laying the finger on the ſore, pointing out the Abominations by name, denouncing the vengeance of God upon them: For, we ſee here how particularly God characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth theſe <hi>Rulers,</hi> laying open all their abominations, ſpeaking to them in wrath: And ſurely this alſo (as the reſt of the Scripture) is written for our inſtruction.</item>
                  <item>2 It's <hi>no wonder</hi> that the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the world are troubled at, and moved againſt the Goſpel of the Kingdome, for here God ſaith, He will ſpeak it to them <hi>in wrath,</hi> and vex them with it in his <hi>ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 It's not ſo much <hi>the infirmities of the Saints</hi> accompanying the delivery of their meſſage to the world, or any other circumſtance about it, that troubles and vexes the <hi>Rulers,</hi> (let them pretend what they will) <hi>as the doctrine it ſelfe,</hi> when it's rightly aſſerted, and thorowly opened, as that which is at hand, and ought to be ſubmitted to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay. O! how doth it trouble and vex them to heare of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of King Jeſus, to depoſe them (of their uſurpations) and take the Kingdome to himſelfe? If it troubled <hi>Herod,</hi> and all <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with him, when they heard of this Kings firſt coming meek and lowly; how then think we, will it not much more trouble the Kings and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the earth to hear of his ſecond coming in power, and the glory of his <hi>Sion?</hi> It cannot be otherwiſe, for God ſaith he will trouble and vex them with an, <hi>I have ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 When the <hi>Rulers</hi> come to this height of ungratefull wickedneſſe, to take counſell againſt the Lord and his anointed, to break their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords from them, <hi>THEN is the time of Gdos wrath come to that Generation;</hi> he will <hi>ſpeake to them in wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 That before ſuch time as God enters into judgement with the reſt of the Kings of the earth, and that Whore (myſtery <hi>Babylon</hi> the great) whom they uphold, God Judges theſe <hi>Rulers;</hi> he ſpeaks to them in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170601:16"/>wrath, to them in particular, to them that <hi>Take counſell againſt the Lord and his anointed.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <q>For the Lord ſhall riſe up as in mount Perazim, he ſhall be wroth as in the Valley of Gibeon, that he may doe his worke, his ſtrange worke; and bring to paſſe his act, his ſtrange act: Awake, awake, put on ſtrength, O arme of the Lord, awake as in the ancient dayes, in the Generations of old.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p n="2">2 Here's the work of Gods love and faithfulneſſe to his Son, in theſe words, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon Sion the hill of my holineſſe:</hi> as it is in the margent of the Bible. <hi>YET have I,</hi> &amp;c. As if God had ſaid, Notwithſtanding your taking counſell againſt him and his anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that you have ſo far proceeded (managing your buſineſſe ſo wiſely, to the very heighth and depth of wiſedome) as to make your ſelves formidable in your owne eyes, thinking you have gotten ſtrength and power ſufficient to put your counſels in practice, crying, <hi>Let us breake their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords from us; yet have I ſet my King upon Sion, the hill of my holineſſe:</hi> Though you take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell againſt him, to make the way to his Kingdome as thorny, difficult, and perillous as you can; though you be ſo ungratefull, and unfaithfull to forſake and take counſell againſt him and his, yet will not I be ſo to my beloved Son, <hi>YET have I ſet my King upon Sion the hill of my holineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet have I ſet MY KING:</hi> Though theſe Rulers will not make him a King, yet God will; <hi>My King,</hi> though they reject him, would <hi>breake his bands,</hi> and <hi>caſt away his cords,</hi> that he might not raigne over them, yet God hath made him a King, and given him a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: He it is, who muſt goe forth conquering and to conquer, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying all his enemies, breaking them to pieces like a Potters veſſel; plucking up every plant that his father hath not planted, throwing downe all thoſe ſuperſtructures that are not of his owne building, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting new Heavens and a new Earth, <hi>A New Creation,</hi> making it a ſuitable purchaſe to the unvaluable price of his blood, clothing it with his glory, that it may be a fit preſent for his father at the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon SION;</hi> That is, the Church of Chriſt, by <hi>Sion</hi> is meant the Church throughout the whole Scripture; that I ſuppoſe is granted by all, therefore I need not enlarge upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon Sion the HILL of my holineſſe.</hi> Why a <hi>hill?</hi> A <hi>hill</hi> is a place of great advantage, on which, if an Army be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170601:16"/>it may be an impoſſible thing for the enemy to diſlodge them: So, God here ſets his King upon his <hi>Hill</hi> (his Church) a place of ſuch advantage, that God doth (if I may ſo expreſſe it) even vaunt it over theſe <hi>Rulers,</hi> that he hath (notwithſtanding their oppoſitions, policies, ſtratagems, and wiſedome) ſet his King upon his <hi>hill,</hi> where he is a naile faſtened in a ſure place, on which all the veſſels may hang ſecure and ſafe; ſuch a place, as his being fixt there, fruſtrates all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, undoes all their contrivements, and brings to naught all their Counſells; it implies ſo much to me, for, it is as if God had ſaid, notwithſtanding you have ſteered a contrary courſe, and taken counſell how to make your ſelves ſtrong, to break my Sons <hi>bands and cords,</hi> and have prevailed very far, that you are even ready to put your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells in execution, crying out amaine for action, <hi>LET <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S;</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon Sion the hill of my holineſſe:</hi> I have done it, and there he is, and now what can you doe? It's impoſſible for you to diſlodge him, for my <hi>hill</hi> is ſtrong, <hi>Its terrible as an Army with banners:</hi> Why a <hi>hill?</hi> if a man be upon a <hi>hill,</hi> he may ſee all round about him; ſo here, God ſets his King upon his hill, that he may from thence take a view of all the motions and contrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, plots and deſignes of his enemies. When the Son is ſeated on this <hi>hill,</hi> thoſe Counſels againſt him and his, which were ſecret and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, in the dark before, (onely the Eagles of the Age, a penetrating eye, could perceive them) are now made manifeſt, and laid open to the view of all, to the ſhame and confuſion of theſe <hi>Rulers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, when a man is ſet on a <hi>hill,</hi> he may be ſeen and heard of all, as <hi>Jotham</hi> was by the men of <hi>Shechem:</hi> So here, God hath ſet his King upon his <hi>hill,</hi> that his glory may be perſpicuous to the whole world, and the publication of his Decrees may be heard farre and neare, that, though when the voyce of the Trumpet ſounds ſhrill, and waxes loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and louder, the people may tremble for fear, yet, the <hi>Moſes's</hi> and <hi>Joſhuah's</hi> may have mountaine diſcoveries of the glory of God, having fellowſhip with the father and the Son, as with a familiar friend.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The hill of my HOLINESSE:</hi> The Kings ſeat is a <hi>hill of holineſſe,</hi> yea, the <hi>hill of Gods holineſſe:</hi> But why a hill of <hi>holineſſe?</hi> why, nothing leſſe then <hi>holineſſe</hi> is a fit qualification for the ſeat of Chriſt; It's not the great names of men, Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Seekers, Non-church-men, above Ordinances; or Chancellors and Vice-Chancellors of Univerſities, Deanes, Maſters and Fellowes of Colledges, Tryers, Parſons and Vicars of Pariſhes, that qualifie men
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170601:17"/>for the work of Chriſt in this day; no, 'tis onely <hi>true holineſſe,</hi> the <hi>holineſſe</hi> (the Image) of God, that onely makes a man a fit ſeat for Chriſt to raigne in, and of which ſoever of the firſt ſort of names of men, they are that have this qualification <hi>[holineſſe]</hi> they are as ſo many ſands or pieces of this <hi>hill of holineſſe,</hi> and out of all theſe God will draw his holy ones, and they ſhall become the <hi>hill of his holineſſe,</hi> and he will ſet his Son there, and he ſhall be their glorious King. The <hi>holineſſe</hi> of this <hi>hill</hi> is the ſtrength of it, were it not a <hi>holy hill,</hi> it might be overcome by the aſſaults and underminings of the enemy. It was the Image of God (which <hi>holineſſe</hi> is) on <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, that made him a rightfull King over the world, and ſtruck ſuch an awe and dread of him into all the Creatures, keeping them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his obedience, but when he loſt that, he loſt all; ſo, it's the <hi>holineſſe of the Church</hi> of Chriſt, this ſeat of the King, that makes it an Impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Fort againſt her Kings Enemies.</p>
               <p>And why <hi>MY HOLINESSE,</hi> the holineſſe of God? All other <hi>holineſſe</hi> is nothing, mans righteouſneſſe is but droſſe and dung, baſe mettall; but that which is <hi>Gods holineſſe,</hi> the holineſſe of God impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us through Chriſt, the Image of that Imprinted on us by the mighty working of the ſpirit of Chriſt, is that which the gates of hell ſhall not, nor cannot prevaile againſt.</p>
               <p>And <hi>MY HOLINESSE;</hi> the <hi>holineſſe</hi> of God is a <hi>perfect holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>be ye perfect as your heavenly father is perfect.</hi> It's not to be holy in part, but to be wholly holy, all over ſanctified; to be holy, ſo, as to be ſet againſt every wickedneſſe, to allow of, or wink at none: It's neceſſary this hill ſhould be cloathed with the <hi>perfect holineſſe</hi> of God, otherwiſe it would be as tender towards the wickedneſſes of men, as moſt profeſſors are at this day, and ſo, not be wholly ſet againſt all wickedneſſes, let them be in what men ſoever, Rulers or people (though cover'd over with never ſo curious a covering) Chriſt their King is, and they muſt be ſo, otherwiſe they are no ſeat for him; <hi>I have ſet my King on the hill of my holineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have SET my King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Set him,</hi> in a poſture becoming a King; <hi>ſet him,</hi> as in a ſeat of Judicature, there ſhall he ſit and judge his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; out of this <hi>hill</hi> the Angels come to poure out the Vials of the wrath of God upon the world: <hi>Set him,</hi> as in Majeſty and glory, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Kings and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the earth, that have ſet themſelves, and taken counſell againſt him and his anointed; here he ſhall ſit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the wonderfull things the love of the father will doe for his glory and honour.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170601:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I have ſet my King;</hi> it's God that ſets Chriſt on <hi>Syon; I have done it,</hi> ſaith God; you thought (and took counſell) to deale wiſely againſt my Son, but I have dealt more wiſely for him, then you could againſt him; you ſeek to hide your counſells from me, and my counſell is hid from yon; you goe in contrary wayes to me, and I ſteer a courſe beyond and contrary to your expectations, and before you are aware bring my purpoſes to paſſe upon you, <hi>I have ſet my King on Sion.</hi> God doth this for his Son, in ſome eminent way, whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears he doth it, and none elſe; that his Son is engaged to him for his exaltation: There's ſome remarkable <hi>unwonted</hi> circumſtance accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies this action, making it eminently evident, to be the work of the finger of God onely; that it's not man, but God himſelfe hath done this; <hi>I have done it,</hi> ſaith God. Upon this, this hill of God is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolidated and ſtrengthened, as that Chriſt from hence declares the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree; hence, the Trumpet ſounds, and all that will not hearken to the voyce thereof, are in great danger of periſhing.</p>
               <p>We ſee here what God doth for his beloved, in the midſt of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and contradictions of men, <hi>He ſets him upon Sion the hill of his holineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Let us hence Obſerve.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In this day of his wrath, God will give the Kingdomes to his Son, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon Sion the hill of my holineſſe;</hi> the Rulers taking counſell, and digging deep to hide it from the Lord, caſting about to find out a way to keep his King from his right, in the midſt of his wrath and fury againſt them for their wickedneſſe, he ſets his King on <hi>Sion;</hi> now, I have done it, ſaith God; he ſpeaks it to them <hi>in his wrath,</hi> and vexes them (with the doing of it) <hi>in his ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</hi> God having overturned the Heathen Emperors, the Popiſh Kings of the earth ſnatch up the Crowne, and ſet it on their head; God overturnes ſome of them, and theſe Apoſtate Rulers faſten the Crowne to their Temples; but their comes a third overturning, which is a thorough one indeed, for ſaith God, <hi>Remove the Diadem, take off the Crowne, this ſhall not be the ſame, exalt him that is low, and abaſe him that is high: I will overturne overturne overturne it, and it ſhall be no more, untill he come whoſe right it is, and I will give it him:</hi> Where are theſe Rulers now? there's no hope for them, for his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is an everlaſting Kingdome.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That while theſe Apoſtate Rulers are taking counſell together againſt the Lord and his anointed, the deſigne of God is then, at that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170601:18"/>time, to ſet his King upon <hi>Sion,</hi> the hill of his holineſſe: And he doth it in oppoſition to them, though they contradict it, <hi>YET</hi> I have done it, ſaith God.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That the firſt thing God doth for his Son, after he hath made bare his arme, and entred into judgement with the Antichriſtian world (for ſurely he began that work, when theſe Rulers cut downe ſome of the Kings of the earth) and in oppoſition to theſe Rulers, is, to make him King in <hi>Sion,</hi> in his Church, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON SION the hill of my holineſſe;</hi> He is ſet there, in a poſture fit for the carrying on the deſigne which he and his father are now managing in the world; there is his Throne, and his holy ones about him; and there he will ſit, and together with them judge the world, and poure downe his fathers wrath upon it.</p>
               <p n="4">4 That <hi>Sion</hi> may be a fit ſeat for the Son to ſettle himſelfe upon, in oppoſition to all his enemies, God makes <hi>Sion</hi> the hill of his holineſſe; <hi>The HILL of my holineſſe;</hi> a <hi>hill,</hi> for ſtrength and ſtability, it's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable; a <hi>hill,</hi> for union, all its parts are ſo united and compact together, as none can divide it; a <hi>hill,</hi> for height, <hi>The mountaine of the height of Iſrael,</hi> it's above the world, reaches up to the Heavens: And a <hi>hill</hi> of holineſſe; the King being ſeated upon this hill, this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphoricall hill becomes his Court, and thoſe in it his Courtiers; they are clothed with the ſame clothing his Majeſty is, <hi>(h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe)</hi> they are all like their Lord; each one of them reſembling the Children of a King, holineſſe to the Lord is written upon them: And a <hi>hill of holines,</hi> for they are conſecrated, ſeparated, and ſet apart for the work of Chriſt at this day, ſanctified for this ſervice; enabled to overcome all the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the evill one, and having done all <hi>to ſtand,</hi> to keep their place and ſtation, a ſeat and Throne for Chriſt, to be ſuch Carpenters as ſhall fray away all the Hornes; the ſpirit of the Hornes ſhall not enter into theſe Carpenters, for God ſaith, <hi>Sion</hi> is the hill of his holineſſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Although at this day, many may fall away, and looſe their firſt love, many prove fooliſh Virgins, yet God hath his true Church, his <hi>hill</hi> of true holineſſe, a fit ſeat for his Son; his choſen number, which he unites together, and by the mighty working of his ſpirit, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the hill of his holineſſe: He ſets his Son upon this hill, and thence he iſſues forth the Decrees of his father about the concernments of his Kingdome, notwithſtanding the power and forces of his enemies againſt him.</p>
               <p n="6">6 That under the Government of theſe Rulers the people of God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170601:18"/>have not liberty to come up to the height of Gods holineſſe, for when they come to be a <hi>hill</hi> of holineſſe, the world ſtands in oppoſition to them, and they unto the world. Chriſt is ſet upon the hill of Gods holineſſe, in oppoſition to the Rulers of the world: If any then blame the followers of the Lamb, as buſie-bodies and raſh ſpirits, ſaying it's otherwiſe with them now, then it was under the Kings, they may be as holy as they will, and live in their fellowſhip with God and Chriſt in his owne Ordinances to the higheſt; it's a falſity, for if they ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the height of Gods holineſſe, (to get to the top of this <hi>hill</hi>) to enjoy the fullneſſe of the Promiſes in Chriſt, by following him fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the voyce of his ſpirit in his word in this day, they are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Rulers, and taken counſell againſt.</p>
               <p n="7">7 We may here ſee what God expects from his <hi>Sion</hi> (his Church) that in this day, when the Rulers and great men of the world reject Chriſt, and take counſell againſt him and his, that this his hill of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhould receive his Son, and cleave ſo cloſe to him, eſpouſe his righteous intereſt ſo unfeignedly and ſo zealouſly, as that it may be a <hi>hill of advantage</hi> whereon Chriſt may ſit as King, in oppoſition to the Kings of the earth, and in deſpite of theſe <hi>Rulers;</hi> although the Kings of the earth ſet themſelves, and the <hi>Rulers</hi> take counſell together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord and his anointed; when the Kings and the <hi>Rulers</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine together to doe their utmoſt, the one by an open perverſe ſetting themſelves, the other by taking counſell (pernicious ſecret counſell) againſt him and his, and at laſt ſhall conjoyne Forces, openly ſetting themſelves to act their counſells; things at this paſſe, God brings his Son to <hi>Sion,</hi> his Church, the <hi>hill</hi> of his holineſſe, he is totally excluded the world, by the men of the world, from having any ſhare in their Royalties, in theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> the father hath tryed the fineſt and pureſt piece of earth the world can ſhew, and finding it falſe, he brings his Son to <hi>Sion,</hi> ſets him there, as in a ſafe place, expecting they will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their necks to his yoke, and their ſhoulders to his burden, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in his goings forth againſt his enemies, after what manner ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be, whitherſoever he will lead them; This indeed is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way to find out an everlaſting reſt, to get a full poſſeſſion of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land, to be bleſſed in heavenly places with him.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Behold, the Lamb with his 144000, his choſen number, ſtanding upon <hi>Mount Sion, having their fathers name written in their foreheads.</hi> (<hi>Sion</hi> is the hill of <hi>my holineſſe,</hi> ſaith God.) Here are the Armies of Heaven, with the great Captaine of Salvation in the head of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170601:19"/>them, in a poſture fit, ready prepared to execute the Decree, <hi>Thou ſhalt breake them with a rod of iron, thou ſhalt daſh them to pieces like a potters veſſell:</hi> But before they enter upon this ſtrange and wonderfull work, being the will of their deare Captaine and leader, they <hi>ſing as it were a new ſong of praiſe</hi> unto God, before the Throne; and though it be a hard ſong that the world cannot learn, and it ſounds harſhly in their eares, ſeeming to them ſuch a thing as never was before, a new invention of the ſpirit of deluſion; yet, theſe choſen holy ones they are acquainted with, and expert in, ſinging this ſong before the Throne of God: Chriſt their Captaine begins, and they follow on, declaring the Decree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>So that now we are come to the work of Chriſt in this day, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what that is, that the Son goeth about as his work in this day of his Fathers wrath: It is, declaring the Decree of his father, as he tells us in theſe words, <hi>I will declare the Decree:</hi> He being thus ſeated on <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the <hi>hill</hi> of Gods holineſſe, he preſently without delay ſends abroad his Heralds, layes his claime, and ſhewes his right and title to the world, the <hi>Decree</hi> of his Father: We may here conſider,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 The <hi>Perſon</hi> declaring.</item>
                  <item>2 The <hi>Declaration</hi> it ſelfe.</item>
                  <item>3 The <hi>Matter</hi> of the Declaration.</item>
                  <item>4 The <hi>Perſons to whom</hi> this Declaration is made.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1 The <hi>Perſons</hi> declaring; <hi>I will declare the Decree;</hi> This is</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Chriſt <hi>Perſonall,</hi> the Mediator <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hriſt Jeſus: That Son of God whom the father hath ſet upon <hi>Sion</hi> the <hi>hill</hi> of his holineſſe, he declares the Decree by his ſpirit in <hi>Sion</hi> among his choſen ones.</item>
                  <item>2 Chriſt <hi>Myſticall;</hi> This cannot reaſonably be denyed, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>A body haſt thou prepared me, then ſaid I, loe I come to doe thy will O God.</hi> Intimating, that it was of neceſſity Chriſt ſhould have a body before he could come to doe the will of his father; It's by this body of his as the inſtrument in his hand, that he fullfills the will of God; ſo, it's by his myſticall body (his Church) that he declares the Decree; doth this his work in this day of his Regement in <hi>Sion:</hi> Further, it's ſaid, <hi>The Law ſhall goe forth out of Sion.</hi> And againe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.27. <hi>What I tell you in darkneſſe, that ſpeake ye in the light; and what ye hear in the eare, that Preach ye upon the houſe top.</hi> Here's the man Chriſt Jeſus teaching his <hi>Sion,</hi> and a command to them to <hi>declare</hi> it publickly to the world; This is that <hi>ſharp ſword going out of his mouth</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he ſmites the Nations.</item>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170601:19"/>
                  <item>2 The <hi>declaration</hi> it ſelfe; <hi>I will DECLARE the Decree: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare</hi> it, how? why, as a Herald declares the Decree of a Prince or State, with ſound of Trumpet, and a loud voyce, in places of greateſt note and reſort, in the moſt open and publick manner that can be, that all may hear, that the Decree may come the eare of every man: So here, <hi>I will declare the Decree,</hi> ſo publickly, upon the houſe top, on the Mount, the Trumpet ſhall ſound ſo ſhrill and loud, that it ſhall pierce the eares of all, yea, of the Kings and Judges of the earth; for, the exhortation to repentance is grounded upon this <hi>Declaration, Be wiſe now therefore,</hi> &amp;c. which could not be a motive to them to repent, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they heard it; And <hi>I will declare the Decree,</hi> lay it all open, make it fully knowne, ſpread it before the underſtandings of men, that none may through ignorance periſh from the way, and looſe that bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I have in my hand to give unto all them that put their truſt in me.</item>
                  <item>3 The <hi>matter</hi> of the Decree; in which we have theſe ſix parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.
<list>
                        <item>1 The <hi>party</hi> decreeing.</item>
                        <item>2 The <hi>Decree</hi> it ſelfe.</item>
                        <item>3 The <hi>means</hi> by which the performance is obtained.</item>
                        <item>4 The <hi>account</hi> or <hi>ſcore</hi> upon which the father doth all this for his Son.</item>
                        <item>5 The <hi>perſon to whom</hi> this gift is given.</item>
                        <item>6 The <hi>time when</hi> God will beſtow this gift.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1 It's the <hi>Lord Jehovah</hi> that makes this Decree: who then can alter, or diſanull it? Shall the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> be unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and ſhall not the Decrees of the great God of Heaven and earth? What folly is it for the world to oppoſe it? What fools-hardineſſe is it for men to fight againſt the Almighty God?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Here's the <hi>Decree</hi> it ſelfe: And therein</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, A <hi>Donation,</hi> or Gift: <hi>I will GIVE thee the Heathen for thine Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion;</hi> It's a Royall gift indeed, fit for a King to receive, and for the glorious God and father of our Lord to beſtow; no leſſe then a whole world; <hi>Heathens for an Inheritance, and utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> O matchleſſe love of a father to a beloved Son! The Heathens that knew him not ſhall become his Inheritance, he will <hi>call upon the Nation that hath not been called by his name to behold him;</hi> he will <hi>be ſought of them that asked not for him, and be found of them that ſought him not;</hi> and the utmoſt parts of the earth ſhall be a habitation for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170601:20"/>him, <hi>to have and to hold,</hi> as the good pleaſure of his father: all things ſhall be put under his feet; <hi>There ſhall be given him Dominion, and glory, and a Kingdome, that all people, Nations, and languages ſhall ſerve him:</hi> And that this gift might be certaine and ſure, that nothing may be able to interrupt his poſſeſſing it, we have in the</item>
                  <item>Second place, The <hi>means</hi> decreed and appointed, whereby he ſhall take this inheritance and poſſeſſion to himſelfe: <hi>Thou ſhalt break them with A ROD OF IRON, and daſh them to pieces like a potters veſſell: Breake them,</hi> take their power, rule, and Dominion away, <hi>breake</hi> their Scepters, and throw downe their Corwnes.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Breake THEM:</hi> who? why, all that in enmity oppoſe him, the raging Heathen, the profane Kings of the earth, and all the Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Saint-like Rulers, that would not have him to raigne over them; them ſhall he break: <hi>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ſhalt breake them;</hi> Chriſt, the Lamb on Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> he ſhall doe it, with his followers, that follow him whitherſoever he goeth: But with what? <hi>With A ROD of iron;</hi> Here is the materiall ſword, the inſtrument with which Chriſt ſhall break all his enemies; <hi>He that killeth with the ſword, muſt be killed with the ſword; they have ſhed the blood of the Saints and Prophets, and he will give them blood to drinke, for they are worthy: Behold, I will make thee a new threſhing Inſtrument, having Teeth: Thou ſhalt threſh the mountaines, and beate them ſmall, and ſhalt make the hills as chaffe:</hi> And <hi>daſh them to pieces like a potters veſſell;</hi> He ſhall break them all to ſhivers, grind them to powder, and make them become as the mire in the ſtreets, and the chaffe of the ſummers threſhing-floore, that the wind ſhall carry them away, and no place ſhall be found for them any more: And he ſhall doe this with as great facil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and eaſe, as a man daſheth a Potters veſſell to pieces; he ſhall have no more trouble in it, then a man hath in daſhing a brittle earthen pot to pieces againſt the ground.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The <hi>means</hi> by which the Son obtaines the performance of this Decree; his interceſſion; <hi>ASKE of me;</hi> It's but ask and have, if the Lord ask his father any thing, he will give it him; if he ask a world, his enemies for an Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſſion, his requeſt is granted; <hi>The father heareth him alwayes,</hi> he neither will nor can deny him what he deſires. <hi>Aske of me the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then for thine inheritance,</hi> and thou ſhalt have them ſaith God, either thy ſlaves or thy free-men, which thou wilt, they ſhall be thine to doe with them as thou pleaſeſt: <hi>Aske of me, the utmoſt parts of the earth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170601:20"/>for a poſſeſſion,</hi> and thou ſhalt have it; if thou wilt have a whole world for thy Court, to entertaine thy followers, thy choſen ones, it's thine: And that the world may be emptied of all thoſe uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, enemies of thine in it, that thou mayeſt take quiet poſſeſſion, <hi>Ask of me, and thou ſhalt break them with a rod of iron, and daſh them to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like a potters veſſell,</hi> ſend them flying into another world to inherit their merited portion with hypocrites and unbelievers: And <hi>ASKE of me, and I will give thee,</hi> &amp;c. If thou wilt have the gift of my love, thou muſt ask it, <hi>ASKE of me;</hi> I will give nothing without asking, therefore come, <hi>Aske of me and I will give thee the Heathen for thine Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Upon what <hi>account</hi> or <hi>ſcore</hi> is it that the father will doe ſo much for this his Son? Why, it's ſolely upon the account of his Son-ſhip; <hi>Thou art my SON, this day have I begotten thee;</hi> therefore now, <hi>Ask of me, and I will give thee,</hi> &amp;c. God will give this gift to none but his Son, and were he not his Son he ſhould not have it; it's a gift too rich and too glorious for any beſides the Son of God, the Heire of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: <hi>Thou art my SON,</hi> ſaid God, and I am engaged as I am thy father, to beſtow a fatherly gift upon thee, and now <hi>Aske of me,</hi> and I will beſtow ſuch a gift upon thee, as becomes my glory to give, and thine honour to receive; <hi>Thou art my SON, this day have I BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GOTTEN thee,</hi> I conceive this is not onely meant of the eternall generation of the Son, nor onely of that day of Chriſts exaltation and honour, when the father raiſed him from the dead, not ſuffering his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one to ſee corruption, making it evident he was the eternall Son of God, a perfect and all-ſufficient Mediator; but alſo of <hi>this day,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God exalteth him as King, and makes him King in <hi>Sion: THIS DAY have I begotten thee,</hi> that is, <hi>this day</hi> have I made it evident to the whole world thou art my Son; I have but now begotten thee as to them, they would not believe before that thou waſt my Son, ſuch a Son, as I have made Heir and King of the world; but now, I have ſet thee on <hi>Sion,</hi> and it being out of all diſpute in <hi>Sion,</hi> that thou art the onely rightfull King (and that I have made thee ſo) they have received thee, thou art ſet as a King there; and there is a ſufficient light held out to the world from thence, of the truth of this, to leave them without excuſe if they ſubmit not to thee; ſo that, as I have begotten thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore times was, now I have begotten thee in this day alſo; and being thou art <hi>my begotten Son,</hi> mine honour is concerned in thine honour, <hi>Aske of me and I will give thee the Heathen for thy inheritance, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170601:21"/>the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 To <hi>whom</hi> is this gift given? To the Son as Mediator, for we ſee it's the fruit of his Interceſſion, <hi>ASKE of me:</hi> And if ſo, then, to him as a repreſentative, a common perſon, and ſo to all thoſe he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents; if it be given to him, then to his alſo, for <hi>Of his fullneſſe we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive grace for grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 What <hi>day,</hi> or <hi>time</hi> is this, wherein God puts on his Son to make ſuch requeſts, and promiſes to doe ſuch great things for him? Why, <hi>THIS DAY,</hi> wherein God notwithſtanding all the oppoſition of the world, and worldly powers (and in particular theſe Rulers) and in wrath to them for it, ſhall ſet his King upon <hi>Sion,</hi> the <hi>hill</hi> of his holineſſe; <hi>this day,</hi> wherein I have begotten thee; ask of me <hi>this day;</hi> and I will <hi>this day</hi> give thee, the Heathen for thy Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion: And <hi>this day</hi> thou ſhalt break them with a rod of Iron, and daſh them to pieces like a Potters veſſell: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this day, wherein thou ſhalt ask it of me.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Let us conſider the <hi>Perſons to whom</hi> this Decree is declared, they are, The Kings and Judges of the earth: Thoſe very Kings and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers (though here called Judges upon a ſignificant account) which ſet themſelves and take counſel together againſt the Lord and his anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: The <hi>Decree</hi> is declared and publiſhed to them, as is undeniably evident, by the <hi>Exhortation</hi> grounded upon the <hi>Decree, Be wiſe now therefore O ye Kings, be inſtructed ye Judges of the earth;</hi> You oppoſe me, ſetting your ſelves, and taking counſell againſt me, but you now heare the unalterable Decree of the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> my father, <hi>Be wiſe now therefore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>From theſe things we may conclude,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 At this day, when Chriſt is ſeated on <hi>Sion</hi> the Hill of Gods Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, there begins a new quarrell between Chriſt and the worlds Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s: He layes his claime to the world, which they ſay is their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and that he hath nothing to doe with it, but with his Church, bidding him keep to his <hi>Sion,</hi> where his God and father hath ſet him, and meddle not with them, for that is out of his ſphere: And out of <hi>Sion</hi> Chriſt declares the Decree, his right and title to the utmoſt parts of the earth, and, that his father hath given him the <hi>Sword of his mouth, and a rod of iron,</hi> to ſmite and break all that oppoſe him, taking poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his fathers Donation; This breeds ſuch jealouſie, wrath, and fury between theſe two Competitors, that never was ſuch a quarrelling day ſince the world had a being; Now the conteſt is between Chriſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170601:21"/>and man, not ſuch (as God hath made uſe of formerly to bring to paſſe his purpoſes) as are between man and man, but it's between Chriſt (who is God) and man, which of theſe ſhall have the <hi>Rule and Government:</hi> Formerly, the world hath had it's coverings, to hide and garniſh over its actions, that they have not appeared in their true colours, and God ſuffered it ſo to be, but now the mask is taken off, they appeare plainly what they are, againſt Chriſt (notwithſtanding all ſpetious pretences whatſoever) to the view of all the world: And as Chriſt deales more roundly with them, ſo will they be more outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and inveterate againſt him, leaving no place for repentance: <hi>I will declare the Decree,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, and <hi>You Kings and Judges of the earth, repent and kiſſe the Son, or you periſh;</hi> This not ſuiting with the high ſpirits of the world, they will yet kick againſt the pricks, perſiſt in their old practice, in perſecution of, and oppoſition againſt the Lord of life and glory.</item>
                  <item>2 That it's the Duty (and ſo no ſin, nor contrary to Goſpel Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Rules) of the anointed of the Lord, thoſe Herralds of his glory that he ſends into the world, (it's the very will of the Father, and of the Son) they ſhould Preach and declare this Decree concerning the Kingdome of the Son fully, according to the due import of <hi>A De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi> in the eares of the whole world, yea, that the Kings and Judges of the earth may heare, and feare, and tremble: If men or Devils in men beſmear them with the ſpurious conceptions of their owne filthy hearts, what matters it? They have the pure water of the word at hand to waſh off all that dirt: It's the work of Chriſt in this day of his fathers love, <hi>(I will declare the Decree)</hi> that which he will doe by his body, his Myſticall Members, and men cannot duely nor rightly charge his holy ones with ſin or folly, in this their obedience to their Lord: It's the work of Chriſt, to declare it in <hi>Sion</hi> by his ſpirit, and it's the work of <hi>Sion</hi> (as the Inſtrument in his hand) to declare it againe to the world, in oppoſition to the <hi>Kings and Rulers</hi> thereof, in their uſurpations upon the Royall intereſt and Prerogative of Jeſus King of <hi>Sion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 That this Declaration is publiſhed in the time of the fathers wrath, neither is this expreſſion of the Sons love without ſome tokens of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure: The world and the powers thereof, have ſo ſlighted, trampled upon, and provoked the Son, as he will not ſpeak one word for them to plead their cauſe with his father; but by his ſilence ſuffers his fathers wrath to break forth, <hi>ſpeaking to them in wrath, and vexing them in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170601:22"/>his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi> The father having by his Almighty power ſet his King on <hi>Sion,</hi> and he being ready to over-run the world with the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his fathers juſt diſpleaſure, his heart being tender, his bowels rowle within him towards poore ſinners, he muſt declare the Decree, with an Exhortation if now at laſt they will come in, ſubmit to him, and he will bleſſe them; yet it's very haſty, and ends with the harſh ſound of a threating, in caſe of a non-ſudden-acceptance, there's a tang of the fathers wrath, and the Sons provoked diſpleaſure goes along with it; the cleareſt ſun-ſhine of this day is clouded with ſymptomes and tokens of wrath and diſpleaſure, then it's no wonder if God judicially throw ſtumbling-blocks in the way of this Generation in this day, that they may not hearken to the voyce of his Son, but ſtumble, and fall, and periſh.</item>
                  <item>4 The father having decreed to give the whole world to his Son, Heathens for an inheritance, and utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; it muſt of neceſſity be, that all the GREAT poſſeſſors of this earthen world, will prove his enemies; and the declaration of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, will ſet the world on fire, fill it with a fiery fury: <hi>The heavens ſhall paſſe away with a great noyſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent heat, the earth alſo and the works that are therein ſhall be burnt up.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 That this is no rebellious nor ſtrange word, but a doctrine beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Goſpel and Goſpel times, to proclaime the War of the Lord againſt all the enemies of Chriſt; it's the mind of the father, for this is part of the Decree which the Son hath engaged to declare, <hi>Thou ſhalt breake them with a rod of iron, and daſh them to pieces like a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters veſſell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 That this day, is a day of great ſupplication and prayer, <hi>ASKE of me,</hi> ſaith God, the father commands to <hi>aske,</hi> upon ſuch an encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging account, as that it provokes Chriſt and his followers to lye hard at the Throne of grace, for the performance of the fathers Promiſes, ſaith God, <hi>ASKE and I will give; ASKE,</hi> or you cannot receive; but <hi>ASKE and I will give thee the heathen for thine inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion:</hi> If God command to <hi>aske,</hi> upon ſuch an account, how can it be but his people will obey with rejoycing, filling the Heavens with their cryes? And can we think Chriſt will not fill the Cenſor with theſe odours, and offer them up upon the Altar as a ſweet perfume to God his father, and then, what voyces! what thunderings! lightnings! and Earth-quakes will this fire
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170601:22"/>from the Altar fill the earth with? Theſe will fill the Vials of Gods wrath, and ſend the Angels out of the Temple to poure them out upon the world.</item>
                  <item>7 Here's a direction for prayer, in this day: It's the will of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the prayers of the Saints ſhould be chiefly, and in the firſt place, for the glory of Chriſt, that he may have <hi>Heathens for an Inheritance, and utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſſion;</hi> And for vengeance, and ability to execute the wrath of God upon the world ſecondarily, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a means to accompliſh the former, by removing lets and hindran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of the way; Their heart in prayer to their father, ought to run out chiefly for the glory of Chriſt; and ſurely, if the world would be converted and turne to God, it would redound much to the honour of our Lord Jeſus, therefore Chriſt undertakes to <hi>declare the Decree,</hi> tells them the whole ſum of the matter, with Exhortation to come in to him, that they may be bleſſed with everlaſting happineſſe; but if they will not hearken to this voyce of love, then, <hi>ASKE, and thou ſhalt breake them with a rod of iron, and daſh them to pieces like a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters veſſell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 In this day the Interceſſion of Chriſt, and ſo the prayers of the Saints, will be of very high concernment, of dangerous conſequence to the world and worldly powers; They reach at no leſſe then the Crowns and Scepters of the world, that the whole world may become the Lord Chriſts, <hi>Heathens for an Inheritance, and utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſſion:</hi> As the Saints formerly prayed againſt the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens rage,</hi> and the Kings <hi>open profaneneſſe,</hi> in ſetting themſelves againſt their Lord; ſo, they now pray as zealouſly againſt the <hi>Clandeſtine cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Counſells</hi> of hypocriticall Apoſtate Rulers; what though the men of the world, and ſome deluded ſincere hearts, call it ſin (and groſſe infirmity at the beſt) leading to rebellion, unwarrantable talking tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to nought but ruine, it matters not, they have the command of the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> for it, <hi>ASKE of me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and I will give thee the Heathens; ASKE of me and I will give thee the utmoſt parts of the earth; ASKE of me and thou ſhalt breake them with a rod of iron, and daſh them to pieces like a potters veſſell: ASKE</hi> theſe things of me, pray for them and I will give them.</item>
                  <item>9 That in this day, the perverſe oppoſition of the worlds Saint-like Rulers to the Lord and his anointed, will prove ſuch, as will compell them, to ask of their father <hi>AN IRON ROD;</hi> ſuch <hi>an iron rod,</hi> wherewith they may <hi>breake their enemies, and daſh them to pieces like a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170601:23"/>potters veſſell:</hi> And if they ask it, he hath promiſed he will give it, and that in their hand it ſhall doe his appointed work; and then woe to the world, for, how great will the Vintage of Gods wrath upon the world be in that day.</item>
                  <item>10 Such prayers are no way contrary to the will and mind of God, nor unſuitable to a Goſpel ſpirit in Goſpel times, for we ſee at this day, wherein Chriſt is taking his Kingdome to ſet forth the Goſpel in all its glory, the Command is, <hi>ASKE of me;</hi> God will be askt for ſuch things, the giving of which ruines this old world, and makes way for the new Heavens and new Earth: <hi>ASKE of me, the Heathens for an inheritance,</hi> the Powers, Crownes, Scepters of the great men of the world, and I will give them to thee; <hi>ASKE of me the utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſſion,</hi> the whole habitable earth for a place to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play thy glory in, and I will give it; <hi>Pray</hi> unto me, againſt the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, their Apoſtacy and wickedneſſes, taking ſecret wylie Counſell, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bining in leagues and agreements together, aſoſiating themſelves with the Kings of the earth againſt the Lord and his anointed, and that, to break their bands, and caſt away their cords; <hi>Cry</hi> aloud unto me againſt them, and theſe their abominable practices, and I will put the iron ſword of my wrath and vengeance into thy hand, and thou ſhalt break them with it, and my ſpirit ſhall ſo aſſiſt thee, by an Almighty opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that there ſhall be as great eaſe and facillity without let or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance in doing this work of my juſt wrath and vengeance, as there is in daſhing a potters veſſel againſt the ground.</item>
                  <item>11 Here is great encouragement to the Saints and people of God to perſiſt and grow valiant in the way of the truth, <hi>of this truth;</hi> Lift up your hearts, cryes, and groanes higher and higher, to your God and father, againſt the enemies of your Lord, and for the glory and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt; for, while you are ſo doing, you are in your fathers way, doing his Command, <hi>ASKE of me,</hi> ſaith he. Againe, you are in the way of the Promiſe, if you <hi>aske,</hi> God hath Promiſed he will give, <hi>ASKE of me and I will give thee;</hi> yea, God ſtands here in a giving poſture, he waites but for a Petition, and when it comes, he anſwers it gratiouſly, he bids you <hi>aske</hi> that he may give; there's a neceſſity you muſt <hi>aske,</hi> ſaith God, I have a gift in my hand worthy a God to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, but you muſt <hi>aske</hi> it ere I can give it, that is the order I have ſet downe to my ſelfe to walk by, and I cannot, it becomes not my wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to recede from it, therefore <hi>ASKE of me and I will give thee the Heathen for thy Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170601:23"/>
                  <item>12 That there will be in this day, a reluctancy and backwardneſſe in the people of God, to the performance of this great duty this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the father layes upon them; which may come to paſſe partly through the <hi>darkneſſe of this day,</hi> the uncertainty and unclearneſſe of things, that they know not what to judge of them, (as hath been opened already;) and partly through that <hi>little betterneſſe in their condition</hi> now to what it was under the Government of the Kings, through carnality of ſpirit being ready to ſit downe there; and partly through <hi>unbelief of heart,</hi> every little hardſhip and difficulty they phanſie to be in the way, they look upon as impoſſibilities, and the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying-glaſſe of unbeliefe, makes them to ſeem ſuch tall and mighty Sons of <hi>Anake,</hi> as God cannot pull downe and overcome; ſo that they are ready to cry out, <hi>Let us make us a Captaine, and returne to our Onyons and Garlicke, and fleſh-pots in Aegypt, for it was better then with us than it is now:</hi> If this were not ſo, this Command <hi>ASKE of me,</hi> were needleſſe, for otherwiſe they would be willing enough and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enough of themſelves, their owne eternall happineſſe and glory is ſo much concerned in it, that it would be a motive ſtrong enough and ſufficient to draw them; but here God is faine to call upon and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his people, <hi>ASKE of me.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13 The time of Gods giving an anſwer and returne to all the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Saints, is now come: God having filled his hand full of bleſſings, he ſtands ready to open it, and ſcatter them downe upon his people, therefore ſaith he, <hi>ASKE</hi> and I will give; <hi>ASKE of me,</hi> that I may give; fill up the meaſure of your prayers, that I may fill up the meaſure of my gifts; I have ſeene, ſaith God, the hard meaſure you have met with from the world for my Sons ſake, how ungratefully and unworthily they have dealt with you, trampling upon you as dung, deriding you as the off-ſcouring and droſſe of mankind; but now, come, <hi>ASKE of me,</hi> and I will give you the reward of all your labour of love, a Crowne of glory for your Crowne of Thornes, a Royall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change indeed: O! how tender hath Chriſt (by preſenting to his open view, the wounds he received, the blood he ſhed, and the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings he underwent) made the heart of his father? He can bear no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he cannot ſtay till his people come and <hi>aske,</hi> but calls upon them, Come my Lambs, <hi>ASKE of me,</hi> and I will give; <hi>ASKE,</hi> that I may <hi>give you the Heathen for an inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſſion:</hi> He that commands to <hi>aske,</hi> promiſes to <hi>give,</hi> this is the <hi>time</hi> of giving, here's the <hi>time</hi> of receiving.</item>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170601:24"/>
                  <item>14 The neceſſity, and mighty force and power of the ſpirit of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; ſaith God, <hi>ASKE of me</hi> that I may give; you muſt <hi>aske</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I give; and <hi>ASKE of me,</hi> and I cannot deny you, but I muſt give you, <hi>Heathens for an inheritance, and utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſſion; ASKE of me,</hi> and I muſt help you, and you <hi>hall breake your enemies with a rod of iron, and daſh them to pieces like a potters veſſell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>15 What a uſefull inſtrument hath God made <hi>Syon</hi> to be to his Son; as <hi>Sion</hi> muſt become the <hi>hill</hi> of Gods holineſſe before ſhe can be a fit ſeat for Chriſt, ſo before Chriſt can be exalted and honoured as King, he muſt be ſeated on <hi>Sion;</hi> he muſt be ſeated as a King there before he is in a fit poſture to declare the Decree of his father, his right and title to the world; and as ſoone as he is ſettled there, he is accompliſht at all points, to encounter with the enemies of his Kingdome, ſends them <hi>a defiance,</hi> a declaration of his right and title to their uſurped poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; <hi>Sion</hi> is his Magazine, out of which he fetches all his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of war, and which he hath made of ſufficient force to blow up and bring to ruine all the foundations of rebellion and oppoſition his enemies have laid againſt him.</item>
                  <item>16 It's worthy our taking notice of, and of confiderable conſequence for us to obſerve, The way of our Lords proceedings in this day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is harneſſing himſelfe for the battel; it's not the way and courſe of the politick inventions, Machiavillian ſtratagems, under-hand-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and by the Maximes of State of this world; but in a noble, plaine, heroick way, like a piece of the trueſt valour that ever drew ſword, <hi>like himſelfe,</hi> ſends forth his Heralds, commands voluntary ſubmiſſion, or elſe gives the challenge, lets them know, there's no way but death, periſhing from the way of bleſſedneſſe.</item>
                  <item>17 That it's the greateſt folly and madneſſe for the Rulers and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the world to oppoſe and fight againſt this praying people; for <hi>they</hi> are not onely againſt them, but the Father the Son and the ſpirit, and all the Hoſt of Heaven are againſt them: As <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid, <hi>They that be with us are more then they that be againſt us,</hi> there's a greater and a ſtronger power with them, than the worldly Rulers can raiſe againſt them, although they could bring up Hell it ſelfe from the deep to ſerve them.</item>
                  <item>18 What a ſad account will thoſe be able to give, who joyne and ſtrike hands with theſe perverſe <hi>Rulers</hi> in this day; alſo, thoſe who have not heart nor courage to ſtand up for the Son againſt theſe <hi>Rulers,</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170601:24"/>and their wickedneſſes; <hi>For whoſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my words, of him ſhall the Son of man be aſhamed, when he ſhall come in his owne glory, and in his fathers, and of the holy Angels.</hi> What ſhame and confuſion of face will ceaſe upon them in that day? If ever there was a time, wherein Chriſt expects his friends ſhould ſtand by him, and plead for him, it's now, in this day ſpoken of in the Text, wherein the <hi>Rulers take ſuch pernicious counſell againſt him,</hi> and thoſe that forſake him now, he will not owne before his father, for we ſee at the latter end of the Pſalme, thoſe that <hi>kiſſe not</hi> the Son, ſubmit not to him, and come under his yoke, <hi>periſh from the way</hi> of bleſſedneſſe; they ſhall receive their portion with thoſe that ſhall come at the laſt day, crying, <hi>Lord Lord open unto us,</hi> and Chriſt ſhall profeſſe he knoweth them not.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>The third and laſt part of our work, is, To conſider the <hi>manner how</hi> Chriſt manageth his work in this day, and that is, with much love and pitty to the ſoules of men, exhorting them to a timely repentance, promiſing bleſſedneſſe to all that hearken to him; Although he hath ſeparated his <hi>Sion</hi> from the world, and made it the Hill of Gods Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a fit ſeat for himſelfe; yet, he cannot be contented to goe with a ſword in one hand to execute his fathers Decree, but he muſt have a Pardon in the other, to beſtow upon all thoſe that will ſubmit and come in unto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be wiſe now therefore, O ye Kings: be inſtructed, ye Judges of the earth. Serve the Lord with feare, and rejoyce with trembling. Kiſſe the Son, leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little. Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe words we have</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 An <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Motives</hi> to provoke men to hearken to it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In the Exhortation we have</p>
               <p n="1">1 The <hi>Perſons exhorted,</hi> and they are chiefly the Kings and Judges of the earth; thoſe very Kings that ſet themſelves, and thoſe very Judges (or Rulers) that take counſell together againſt the Lord and his anointed: But though the Exhortation be chiefly to the Kings and Judges, yet not <hi>excluſive</hi> to others, for we find in the laſt clauſe of the Pſalme, <hi>Bleſſedneſſe</hi> promiſed to <hi>all them</hi> that put their truſt in the Son; which <hi>ALL</hi> takes in more then the Kings and Rulers, yea, <hi>ALL</hi> men of what rank and condition ſoever that put their truſt in him, ſhall be bleſſed; and it muſt of neceſſity follow, the Exhortation is of as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170601:25"/>large an extent as that <hi>ALL,</hi> for the Promiſe is brought in as a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to provoke to a hearty embracing of, and hearkening to it.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Here's the <hi>matter</hi> of the Exhortation: which is,</p>
               <p n="1">1 To <hi>get a true and an exact knowledge of God and his wayes, in this their day:</hi> Which is held out unto us in two expreſſions, <hi>WISE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOME</hi> and <hi>INSTR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTION.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be WISE now therefore O ye Kings:</hi> O you prophane Kings, that having a whores forehead and a face of braſſe, without ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe have ſtood up, and ſet your ſelves publickly, wilfully, with all your might againſt-me-without a cauſe, to keep me from my rightfull inheritance, and to prevent my entring my poſſeſſions, the Copy-hold my father hath given me: <hi>Be wiſe now THEREFORE;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? why, you have heard the Decree of my father, the Juſtice and Equity of my right and Title to my Kingdome; I have askt it, and he hath given it me, who hath right and power to give it, he that made it hath given it to me: And my father having ſet me on <hi>Sion</hi> the Hill of his Holineſſe, I am prepared to encounter you, I will waite your lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure no longer; therefore now be <hi>wiſe,</hi> know, conſider what you have to doe, if you reſiſt and ſtand it out, there's no way but periſhing and death; but if you ſubmit your ſelves unto, and put your truſt in me, I will bleſſe you, make you really happy; here's life and death ſet before you, be <hi>wiſe</hi> now in your choyce, that you may live and not dye: Be <hi>wiſe</hi> with the wiſedome of God wherein is life, for why will ye dye? You are Kings, and it's a hard leſſon for you to be willing to part with your great poſſeſſions, and become Beggars, but learne it, and you ſhall find wiſedome it ſelfe in ſuch ſeeming folly; <hi>Whatſoever any man forſakes for my ſake, I will give it him againe in my Kingdome with great advantage,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; Be <hi>wiſe,</hi> know and conſider the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> my father, and what he hath already done for me; know and conſider <hi>me</hi> alſo, what I am to doe to, and in the world, as the will of my father in this day of his great wrath and fury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be INSTR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTED ye Judges of the earth:</hi> Ye <hi>Judges,</hi> you that have ſet your ſelves above the rank, and your feet on the neck of Kings, that would be accounted <hi>repairers of the breaches, and reſtorers of the paths to dwell in;</hi> and yet take counſell againſt the Lord and his anointed, to break their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords from you; you <hi>Judges,</hi> that carry it ſo underhand and ſecretly againſt me and mine, while you ſeem to be for me, pretending a <hi>kiſſe,</hi> when you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a blow under the fifth rib, that you need not ſtrike a ſecond time:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170601:25"/>Come you <hi>Judges be INSTR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTED,</hi> know the wickedneſſe and folly of your malicious wayes, they will yield you nothing but vanity and vexation of ſpirit, the beſt fruit they can preſent you with is tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for, this Proverb ſhall be taken up againſt you, <hi>The Lord hath broken the ſtaffe of the wicked, and the Scepter of the Rulers,</hi> yea, <hi>Tophet is ordained of old, yea, for the King it is prepared, he hath made it deepe and large, the pile thereof is fire and much wood, the wrath of the Lord like a ſtream of brimſtone doth kindle it: ye Judges of the EARTH;</hi> though you have ſet your ſelves in the higheſt forme, and will not be numbred among the Kings of the earth, but preſent your ſelves to the world as <hi>Rulers,</hi> your Authority and Government to be of my fathers appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and according to his will; yet, be <hi>inſtructed</hi> in this, know this, that you and your inventions are of the earth, earthy; though you will not be Kings of the earth, yet you are Judges of the earth, though the moſt refined, yet ſtill but earth; you, your wayes, and inventions, are not of, nor from heaven, but of and from the earth: Be <hi>inſtructed</hi> ye Judges of the earth in the wiſedome of God, in the ſervice, worſhip, and out-goings of God in this your day, you have been cunning and wiſe Counſellors for your ſelves, and in your own wayes and concernments; be ye now <hi>inſtructed,</hi> become as wiſe and knowing in the ways and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of God and his Son in this your day: <hi>Be wiſe ye Kings, and be inſtructed ye Judges of the earth,</hi> hearken unto me or you periſh from the way of life and bleſſedneſſe, and goe into eternall death and miſery.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To <hi>worſhip the true God, and him onely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling;</hi> Here's both ſervice done to God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in God; and they are exhorted to mix the one with fear, and to mingle trembling with the other, and then they will be in the way of the Promiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2. <hi>To this man will I looke, even to him that is poore, and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my word.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.1. &amp; 145.191. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his Commandements. He will full fill the deſire of them that feare him, he alſo will heare their cry, and will ſave them. But unto you that fear my name, ſhall the Son of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ariſe, with healing in his wings; and ye ſhall goe forth, and grow up as the Calves of the ſtall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 To <hi>a hearty ſubmiſſion to the Son in this way the father hath ſet him;</hi> giving him that honour and thoſe dues, the father hath decreed he ſhall have; <hi>KISSE THE SON;</hi> this <hi>kiſſe</hi> gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170601:26"/>the moſt abſolute ſubjection that is poſſible; not that which is onely of the outward man, through fear and inability to reſiſt, but that, which is from the heart, and the fruit of the ſtrongeſt love, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the beſt and ſureſt Baſis of the higheſt reaſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Lord gives the world ſeverall <hi>Motives</hi> to provoke them to hearken to his advice and Counſell. And they are</p>
               <p n="1">1 The <hi>Conſideration of the Sons anger; Kiſſe the Son leaſt he be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry:</hi> All the day long hitherto we were exhorted to repentance and ſubmiſſion to the Son, from the conſideration of his love and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſſe to ſinners, but now we are call'd upon with a <hi>Leaſt he be angry;</hi> The day of Gods judging this Generation, and putting the Decree in execution, the time for the full performance of his Promiſes to his choſen ones, is come, and now Chriſts heart is ſo full of love to his ſuffering ones, that have been ſo long trampled upon by the world, that he is ſo intenſe upon giving out the gifts of his father (their Crowne) to them, that he will not tarry nor waite long, but his anger will be kindled, and then there followes nothing but <hi>woe, periſhing, death:</hi> And <hi>leaſt he be angry,</hi> it ſtrongly implies, that he will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and angry to the purpoſe with all thoſe that will not readily and quickly hearken to him, inflicting no leſſe puniſhment upon them than <hi>periſhing,</hi> eternall death.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The <hi>Conſideration of the ſad condition we ſhall be in, if his wrath be kindled but a little: and ye periſh from the way, When his wrath is kindled but a little:</hi> Here's a periſhing woe; now his wrath is kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled and kindled but a little, there's no way but death; how dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous is it to provoke the Son in this day, when a little kindling of his wrath will periſh our ſoules! How ſtrongly ought this to work upon us, to move us to make haſt and meet him in the way, leaſt his wrath be kindled but a little, and he accuſe us to the Judge, not owning us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his father, and our portion be to periſh with the hypocrite and unbeliever:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And periſh from the way;</hi> another piece of the Motive, and an ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of our ſin if we hearken not to it; While this Exhortation ſounds in our eares, we are in the way to happineſſe, the day of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not quite ſpent and gone, the night hath not yet totally ceazed upon us, but, if our dull and ſtubborne hearts, by not cloſing with his gratious motions, kindle his wrath but a little, we periſh, the day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is cut off from us, the night of judgement and wrath ceazes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and we are undone for eternity.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170601:26"/>
               <p n="3">3 A <hi>Promiſe of Bleſſedneſſe; Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him:</hi> Here's love indeed! Come, ſubmit to me, put your truſt in me, and I will bleſſe you; if the conſideration of my aptneſſe to be angry in this day, and how dangerous it is to have my wrath kindled but a little, if this will not move you, but you rather (though unworthily and irrationally) count me a hard Maſter; yet, let this prevaile with you, that you ſhall get no leſſe than <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> by truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in me, yea, none ſhall goe without it, but <hi>all they</hi> that truſt in me ſhall be bleſſed; yea, and be bleſſed with the higheſt bleſſings, <hi>with all ſpirituall bleſſings in heavenly places;</hi> yea, with <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> in the abſtract, <hi>BLESSED are all they that put their truſt in me;</hi> bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe, the Fountaine of bleſſedneſſe ſhall be their Portion: And now come, come and be bleſſed, made really happy; if you will not hearken to this, I have nothing more to ſay, <hi>Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him;</hi> With theſe words the bleſſed Lamb of God cloſes up his mouth, and goeth about his fathers work.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>From hence we may Obſerve,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 That although this Decree be concerning the total Amotion of all the Kingdomes of this world, and their being given to the Lord Chriſt, yet, it muſt be declared <hi>with abundance of love to the ſoules of men,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting all to repentance and ſubmiſſion to the Son, that they may be bleſſed.</item>
                  <item>2 That <hi>None are exempted</hi> (no not the greateſt of ſinners) <hi>from the benefit of this Exhortation;</hi> For, our Lord directs his ſpeech chiefly and in the firſt place to his greateſt enemies, the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Judges of the earth,</hi> that ſet themſelves and take counſell together againſt him and his, <hi>Be wiſe O ye Kings, be inſtructed ye Judges of the earth:</hi> What encouragement is here to all and the greateſt of ſinners to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto this voyce, and come under his healings, and they ſhall be bleſſed?</item>
                  <item>3 We may here behold <hi>The abundant riches of free grace, and the immenſe greatneſſe of the love of Chriſt to ſinners;</hi> That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great and unheard of aggravations of the ſins of the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the world at this day, yet he will have them exhorted and woed to come in unto him, that they may be bleſſed by him; yea further, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this day is a day of great wrath, and the world have ſo provokt him as he cannot find in his heart to intercede for them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his father in wrath enquire into their actions; yet with what love and grace and ſtrong perſwaſions, doth he exhort men to come
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170601:27"/>and ſubmit to him that he may bleſſe them? He cannot be contented to ſee the worlds ruines, and the deſtruction of ſoules, before he hath made one Eſſay more, pleading with the world to conſider their preſent and future condition, and accept of him upon his owne Tearmes, that he may give <hi>Bleſſedneſſe</hi> to them; yea, though the wickedneſſe of this world in this day be ſuch, that it's <hi>flint hard,</hi> and made ſo by <hi>love and mercy,</hi> that our Lord is forc't to make a change, alter his voyce, from expreſſions and conſiderations of love, to a threatning of, and pointing to his direfull anger, to try how that may work; yet knowing it's not the naturall tendency of ſuch a voyce to work thorowly upon the hearts of men, his love cloſes with a bleſſed Promiſe of bleſſedneſſe; as he began his work here on earth (in the dayes of his fleſh) with wonderfull unparallel'd expreſſions of love, ſo, will he finiſh his work here with the ſame glory, he concludes with a large Promiſe of rich bleſſedneſſe! How tender is the heart of Chriſt! He ſpeaks but two or three words that have ſymptomes of wrath and diſpleaſure in them, he hides his gracious and loving countenance but a moment, and he can containe no longer, but he muſt unvaile himſelfe and appear in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Mediatorſhip; It is, as if he had ſaid, <hi>I have exhorted you to come and kiſſe me, to ſubmit to me leaſt I be angry, and you periſh from the way, but that hath but little operation upon you, therefore now I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play my glory before you; doe but come to me, believe on me, truſt in me, depend and relye upon me onely and alone for happineſſe, forſake all your Idolls, and every thing that is grievous and contrary to me, and I will bleſſe you; doe but truſt me and I will doe it, the father hath given me power to doe it, and by that power I am able to doe it, and my blood ſhall ſpeake the willingneſſe of my heart to doe it, Who ever ſhed his blood for his enemies (ſuch enemies) but I? and if I had not lov'd them with ſuch a love as would give them the greateſt bleſſings, I would never have done it; And not one that doth thus truſt and believe in me ſhall goe without the bleſſing, all they that truſt in me ſhall be bleſſed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 That though theſe Kings and Rulers be guilty of moſt abominable wickedneſſe beyond all that ever were before them, ſuch as moves God to ſpeak in wrath to them, yet, <hi>There's hope of life and ſalvation for them, if they will hearken to the Goſpel of the Kingdome</hi> while it's Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to them in this Exhortation, and kiſſe the Son before his wrath be kindled but a little.</item>
                  <item>5 That in this day of the fathers wrath, <hi>Nothing leſſe than a hearty and thorow ſubmiſſion to the Son will pleaſe him,</hi> and prevent his wrath
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170601:27"/>breaking forth to our deſtruction; <hi>KISSE the Son leaſt he be angry.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 It's <hi>No Treaſon againſt the Royall Law of King Jeſus,</hi> whatever it may be againſt the Lawes of men, <hi>to ſeeke to draw men from their obedience to theſe wicked Kings and perverſe Rulers, to kiſſe the Son that</hi> they may be bleſſed with his everlaſting bleſſings.</item>
                  <item>7 That <hi>Men muſt be inſtructed in the wiſedome of God, and be filled with the graces and ſtrength of the ſpirit,</hi> before they can be inabled to come under the happy influence of this bleſſed Promiſe, for we ſee, that in order to this ſubmiſſion to the Son, men are exhorted to be filled with wiſedome and inſtruction, to ſerve the Lord with fear, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce with trembling, and then <hi>Kiſſe the Son,</hi> put your truſt in him, and you ſhall be bleſſed.</item>
                  <item>8 That <hi>in this day,</hi> notwithſtanding the cunning deceits and curious coverings of the Rulers, yet, <hi>the Kings and Rulers of the earth, and King Jeſus, are ſo diametrically contrary to each other, in all their wayes and ſtations, as that it is impoſſible for a man to ſerve them, and be a friend to Chriſt;</hi> The Exhortation is, <hi>Kiſſe the Son,</hi> that is, <hi>kiſſe</hi> none but him, give no obedience but to him, yield ſubjection to none but to him alone, <hi>Come out of her my people,</hi> come from under obedience to the worlds and Antichriſts Kings, Rulers, and Lawes, and become the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Chriſt, ſubmit to the Scepter of the Son; <hi>Kiſſe the Son,</hi> and then you ſhall be bleſſed.</item>
                  <item>9 That this Exhortation with the Decree, is indeed and in truth no other <hi>but the Goſpel of the Kingdome,</hi> the fore-runner of it; which is Preached to the world immediately before it's brought into the world, to move them to ſubmit to it when it comes, and to call the choſen of God out of the world, to prepare themſelves to meet their Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome.</item>
                  <item>10 That this Goſpel of the Kingdome <hi>muſt chiefly and in the firſt place be Preached to the Kings, Rulers, and Magiſtrates of the world:</hi> Our Lord directs his ſpeech firſt to them, <hi>Be wiſe yee Kings, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed yee Judges of the earth:</hi> It muſt be preached to them in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; it's Preached to the reſt of the world as it were by the by, they are put into the little word <hi>all,</hi> at the very cloſe of the Exhortation; therefore, how little cauſe will the Kings and Rulers of the world have, to be wroth and angry with the Saints and people of God, for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this doctrine to them, although it ſound ſo dreadfully in their eares? You ſee their Authority, they doe but their duty in it, to follow their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170601:28"/>Lord, and the dictates of his ſpirit, who hath undertaken this work; and they ſhould periſh together with you, if they ſhould hold their peace, and break the Command of their Lord: And their end is onely, that you may be bleſſed if you hearken to it; what a mighty aggravation of your ſin will this be, if you perſecute, oppoſe, and take counſell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this doctrine, and the publiſhers of it? The wrath of the Son will be kindled againſt you, and when it's kindled but a little, you periſh from the way preſently, and that inevitably without remedy.</item>
                  <item>11 The time of the Preaching this Goſpel, <hi>Is the evening of the Goſpels repenting day;</hi> The Son of righteouſneſſe is now ſetting apace (as to ſinners) and he will ariſe againe with healings in his wings <hi>one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> to thoſe that put their truſt in him; If this voyce be not hearkened to, his wrath will be kindled, and all his enemies ſhall periſh from the way of Bleſſedneſſe; there's no longer day for repentance, they have loſt the bleſſing, and though with <hi>Eſau</hi> they ſhould ſeek it with teares, they ſhall find no place for it; they ſhall hear this voyce no more, but another, <hi>Depart from me yee workers of iniquity, I know you not;</hi> after this voyce ceaſes, there remaines nothing but a fearfull looking for of Judgement: Therefore, it highly concernes the whole world, with their <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> to be cautious how they ſtop their eares, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this wiſe Charmers charming; ſurely if they doe, what horrors! what terrors! what a maſſie weight of wrath of the Almighty God! what unexpreſſible miſery will be our portion for ever? How uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivably unſufferably tormenting, all our long day of eternity, will the recounting over all thoſe opportunities (and eſpecially this) we have had, to make our peace with the jealous God, and to get Chriſt to be our friend by an eaſie ſubmiſion to him upon his owne tearms, be? This will be no ſmall Worme gnawing our conſciences to all eternity.</item>
                  <item>12 It's worthy our Obſervation, That notwithſtanding thoſe ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of wrath and diſpleaſure that appear here and there throughout the Exhortation, <hi>Yet our Lord will have it end full of grace and love, with a Promiſe full of bleſſedneſſe,</hi> Though this Exhortation be made in a day of wrath, and accompanied with wrath, yet, <hi>at evening time it ſhall be light,</hi> the cloſe of this day ſhall be with a very clear Goſpel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the good will of God unto the ſoules of men, ſo that if they hearken not unto him now, they ſhall for ever after hold their peace, be left without the leaſt excuſe, not have a piece of a word to ſay for themſelves, although the wrath of God break forth upon them, periſhing and deſtroying their ſoules with eternall death.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170601:28"/>
            <head>The great Correſpondency this Interpretation holds with other Scriptures that have relation to our times.</head>
            <p>Now it remaines that I ſhould doe theſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Shew that <hi>great correſpondency,</hi> this Scripture with the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation given of it, holdeth with other Propheticall Scriptures that have ſpeciall relation to theſe laſt dayes.</item>
               <item>2 Give my opinion and judgement (according to the light the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights hath given to me) <hi>where abouts we (in this our day) are;</hi> that we may conſider and know our work, God expects at our hands.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt, This Pſalme (according to the following compariſon) is contemporary with the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Pſalme 2. From Verſ. 6. to the end.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Revelation 14. From Verſ. 1. to Verſ. 8.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>YEt have I ſet mine anointed upon Sion the hill of my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> as the Margent hath it. <hi>I will declare the Decree, the Lord hath ſaid unto me, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee. Aske of me, and I ſhall give thee the Heathen for thy inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion. Thou ſhalt break them with a rod of iron, thou ſhalt daſh them in pieces like a potters veſſell.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ANd I looked, and loe a Lamb ſtood on the Mount Sion, and with an hundred forty-foure thouſand having his fathers name written in their foreheads. And I heard a voyce from heaven, as the voyce of many waters, and as the voyce of a great thunder: And I heard the voyce of Harpers, harp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their Harps. And they ſung as it were a new ſong before the Throne, and before the foure Beaſts, and the Elders, and no man could learne that ſong, but the one hundred forty-foure thouſand, which were redeemed from the earth; theſe are they which were not defiled with women; for they are Virgins: Theſe are they which follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170601:29"/>Theſe were redeemed from among men, being the firſt fruits unto God, and to the Lamb: and in their mouth was found no guile: for they are without fault before the Throne of God.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Be wiſe now therefore, O yee Kings: be inſtructed, yee Judges of the earth; ſerve the Lord with feare, and rejoyce with trembling: Kiſſe the Son, leaſt he be angry, and yee periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little, bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>And I ſaw another Angel fly in the midſt of heaven, having the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Goſpel to preach unto them that dwell on the earth, and to every Nation, and Kindred, and Tongue, and People: Saying with a loud voyce, Feare God, and give glory to him; for the houre of his judgement is come; and worſhip him that made heaven and earth, and the Sea, and the fountaines of waters.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>In the Pſalme the Holy Ghoſt ſhewes us, <hi>the ſpetiall and peculiar posture,</hi> the Son of God ſhall ſtand in at that Time, upon <hi>Sion</hi> the hill of Gods Holineſſe, with the work he will then doe in his <hi>Sion; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Decree</hi> to them: In the <hi>Revelation,</hi> the ſame Spirit tells us, <hi>the particular qualifications</hi> of this hill of Holineſſe, on which the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſet his Son, with the work the one hundred forty-foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand being ſo qualified fall to among themſelves; after the example of their Lord, they <hi>ſing a new ſong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, In the Pſalme, the ſpirit of God deſcribes the Preaching of the Goſpel of the Kingdome; in a <hi>ſpeciall and peculiar manner to the Kings and Rulers of the earth:</hi> In the <hi>Revelation</hi> the Holy Ghoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciphers to us the Preaching of the ſame Goſpel, <hi>in relation to the whole world in generall;</hi> The Exhortation to the Kings and Rulers, and the Goſpel Preached to them that dwell on the earth, is one and the ſame: Theſe two Scriptures thus compared together, are an exact Comment upon each other.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170601:29"/>
            <p>The Pſalme cloſes with an Exhortation, the preaching this Everlaſting Goſpel: This 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> goes on, ſhe wes us the work the Son doth being ſeated on <hi>Syon,</hi> having his 144000 about him; after he hath declared his fathers Decree, after the everlaſting Goſpel is preached; he deſtroyes <hi>Babilon,</hi> layes that proud and lofty one in the duſt; pronounces them curſed, and ſubjects of his fathers eternall wrath, that worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and receive his Mark in their forehead and hand, bleſſes them (according to the laſt clauſe in the Pſalme) that dye in the Lord: Yea, proceeds to ſhew us his compleating Acts, his Reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the harveſt, and Treading the Wine-preſſe of his fathers wrath.</p>
            <p>Now if any ſhould be deſirous to know further of the Time, when God will <hi>ſet his King upon Sion</hi> the hill of his holineſſe, and when the Lamb will <hi>ſtand on Mount Sion</hi> with his 144000 about him; I judge, the father will doe that for his Son, in that <hi>ſpace of Time between the powring out of the third and fourth Vialls;</hi> and the declaration of the Decree, with the Exhortation annexed; and the preaching the Everlaſting Goſpel, will end (if not before, yet) with the finiſhing Time of the fourth Viall: My Reaſon is:</p>
            <p>Becauſe, The declaration of the Decree, with the Exhortation to the Kings and Judges of the earth, is the product of the Sons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet on <hi>Sion</hi> as King; and the preaching the Everlaſting Goſpel, is the fruit of the Lambs ſtanding on <hi>Mount Sion</hi> with his 144000 ſinging their new ſong; now the end of all being to bring men to repentance, exhorting them to turne to the true God, worſhip him onely, and ſubmit to the Son that they may be bleſſed by him; and this being a reall act in God, intending the ſalvation of men, it cannot be but all this muſt be done before the day of repentance and ſalvation is finiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and gone; <hi>when the night cometh no man can worke;</hi> and if ſo, then it muſt of neceſſity be granted alſo, that theſe things muſt be done before the fourth Viall is powered out; for, after that Viall is once gone forth, there remaines no place for repentance, the day of repentance and ſalvation is ſpent and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170601:30"/>gone; for the Text expreſly ſaith, that <hi>men blaſphemed the name of God, and repented not to give him glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the two Witneſſes riſe (which we have good ground to believe will be at or before the powring out of the fourth Viall) and execute ſome part of the wrath and judgements of God, the day of repentance and ſalvation being not yet paſt over and gone, it's recorded, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13.) that <hi>the remnant of men left gave glory to the God of heaven,</hi> a true and excellent fruit of true repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; but here, the day of repentance and ſalvation being finiſht, and mens hearts hardened, that is recorded alſo, that <hi>men blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and repented not to give him glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this 14th of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> immediately upon the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Goſpel, <hi>Babilon (Rome) falls;</hi> and ſuddenly upon the neck of that, God by the mouth of an Angel, pronounces them <hi>curſed</hi> (without remedy) <hi>that then worſhip the Beaſt, and his Image, and receive his marke;</hi> and the Son of man followes with his <hi>ſharp ſickle, reaps his harveſt, and gathers the Vine of the earth, treads the wine-preſſe of the wrath of God:</hi> What God may doe in a more than ordinary way, with any particular ſoule, I leave it, but there's no generall Time of repentance and ſalvation, interveening theſe executions of the wrath of God, when once the fourth Viall is powred out: Not being able to anſwer theſe Reaſons, I am fully perſwaded to believe the truth of this Aſſertion. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Daniels little ſtone's ſmiting,</hi> and the <hi>riſe of the two Witneſſes,</hi> be not contemporary with <hi>Davids hill of Sion,</hi> and <hi>John's Mount Sion,</hi> Chriſt being ſeated on it; whether <hi>all theſe Prophecies</hi> will not be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled at one &amp; the ſame time; yea, whether they ſignifie not to us one and the ſame thing, onely, one, one part of the work of God at that day, another, another part of it, I leave to the ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and narrow ſcrutiny of the godly wiſe at this day.</p>
            <p>And let none be diſcouraged from believing theſe things, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the unlikelineſſe of them to come to paſſe in our dayes;</hi> for, the flood of Gods wrath upon the old world, was as unlikely to that worlds underſtanding, to overflow when it did, as theſe things can be to this, and the Scripture ſaith, the <hi>coming of the Son of man
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170601:30"/>ſhall be like unto thoſe dayes.</hi> Againe, the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He ſhall come at midnight,</hi> a time when men (aſleep) leaſt expect him: And againe, <hi>When they that dwell upon the earth ſhall be in the height of their mirth and jollity. F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL OF PEACE, rejoycing and ſending gifts one to another, then the ſpirit of life from God enters into the two Witneſſes, and fills thoſe rejoycing earthen ſoules with great feare, brings an Earth-quake, ſlayes a part of the world, and affrights the remnant that are left, extorting from them glory to the God of heaven:</hi> Yet againe, though the whoriſh woman <hi>Babylon, may come to ſuch proſperity, as to ſay in her heart, I ſit a Queen, and am no Widdow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow, her plagues ſhall come in one day, death, and mourning, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with fire, for ſtrong is the Lord who judgeth her:</hi> Let our hearts ponder theſe things, and we ſhall trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as the word of God, for judgement is at the doore.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, I am to give my judgement <hi>how far we are come at this day,</hi> or rather, <hi>how neare the great God in his providence is come to us,</hi> at what part of this Pſalme thus expounded, we may lay our finger, and ſay, this is our ſtate and condition, this is the work God would have us to doe in this our day; To doe this is a great work, but to doe it with demonſtration to convince the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings of men, and ſtop the mouth of the gain-ſayer, is a far greater work, which I deſpaire to performe; yet, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of light the Lord hath given me, I ſhall make an Eſſay towards a clear evidencing of the Truth.</p>
            <p>I conceive <hi>We are come to the dawning of that day, wherein God will in wrath to the worlds Rulers, ſet his King upon Sion the hill of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; and the Lamb will ſtand on Mount Sion with his</hi> 144000 <hi>(his choſen ones) about him;</hi> wherein the Son will declare the Decree, and the 144000 will be <hi>ſinging their new ſong before the Throne of God, according to the import of that Command of the father to his Son in this ſecond Pſalme, ASKE OF ME?</hi> And that <hi>the preſent Kings and Rulers of the world</hi> (but eſpecially the Rulers who are the head of this gathering together againſt the Lord and his anointed) <hi>are thoſe againſt whom the father will engage in this day of his wrath and jealouſie for his Son, ſpeaking to them in wrath, and vexing them in his ſore diſpleaſure, even with this, his ſetting his King upon Sion the hill of his holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reaſons for this my Aſſertion, are</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170601:31"/>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Becauſe we are already gotten under</hi> (if not towards the latter end of) <hi>the third Viall;</hi> to prove this, that it may be as valid a reaſon to you, as it is to me, I intreat thee Courteous Reader, let thine eyes, accompanied with thy mind, take a journey through Mr. <hi>Tillinghaſt's</hi> Treatiſe upon the Vialls, where you will finde ſo much Reaſon, and ſuch ſtrong Arguments for this aſſertion, as I preſume will be ſo ſatisfactory, as it will not be expected I ſhould ſay any thing more to the point: And if ſo, then upon my former proofe, it appears, the dawning of this day of bleſſedneſſe to the Saints, and of wrath to the world with its Rulers, hath ceazed upon us: But,</item>
               <item>2 <hi>The firſt fruits of the qualifications of Gods hill of holineſſe, Chriſts</hi> 144000; <hi>the ſprinklings of the ſpirit of that day; the beginnings of Chriſts being received as King in Sion, are to be found in the midſt of a deſpiſed people among us in this our day.</hi> Let us view over the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of Chriſts 144000, conſider them, and put on a paire of thoſe excellent ſpectacles made of pure love, and our dim eyes will not behold men like Trees, but, like the purchaſed inheritance of the Son, qualified according to the Decree, to ſuch and ſuch a work, at ſuch a time; I ſay, the firſt fruits, the beginnings of theſe (though yet imperfect) will appeare plainly to our view: And let us with ſimplicity and ſingleneſſe of heart, look out at the Caſements of our ſoules, and we ſhall behold the ſprinklings of the ſpirit of that glorious day; The work of the day ſhewes us the ſpirit of the day; The Saints in that day <hi>ſing a new ſong be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of God,</hi> &amp;c. which is ſuch a ſong as is ſo uncouth, ſo ſtrange to, ſo contrary and above the nature, Principles, and reaſon of the world, as they cannot learne it; no man without this hill of holineſſe, none but the 144000 can learne to ſing this ſong: What is this ſtrange ſong that is ſo hard to be learnt? Why, conſider it, and you will find it to be the Decree, the Son in the ſecond Pſalme undertakes to declare: If we conſider this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar alſo, we ſhall find plainly to appeare in this our day, ſome ſprinklings, the beginnings of the mighty workings of this ſpirit. Let us yet make a ſtand, and conſider the temper and ſpirit of the Lords people in this our day, and we ſhall find Chriſt to have a little footing on <hi>Sion</hi> already; his 144000 begin to look upon him, to conſider him as their King, and their hearts are cleaving to him apace: If we conſider theſe things, we ſhall behold an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170601:31"/>of a glorious fabrick to be erected in its due ſeaſon; which cannot be far off, for when <hi>the ſinging of Birds is heard,</hi> they fly chirping from bough to bough, it's a ſigne <hi>the winter is paſt, and the ſpring is come:</hi> Now is the Time, in which Chriſt will (or doth) call to his beloved, <hi>Riſe up my love, my faire one, and come away:</hi> Follow me. <hi>O my Dove! that art in the clefts of the rock, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret place of the ſtaires</hi> (Gods hiding-place for his people in a day of wrath) <hi>Let me ſee thy countenance, let me heare thy voyce: For ſweet is thy voyce, and thy countenance is comely. Take us the Foxes, the little Foxes</hi> (thoſe that are leſſe diſcernable, and leaſt miſtruſted to doe miſchief) <hi>that ſpoyle the Vines, for our Vines have tender Grapes,</hi> Cant. 2.10, 11, 12.</item>
            </list>
            <p>What though this Kingdome of Heaven be now but as a graine of Muſtard-ſeed, the ſmalleſt of graines, yet it's water'd with the dewes of the ſpirit, and it will, it ſhall grow up to a Tree able to give ſhelter to the Fowles of Heaven. <hi>Elijah's</hi> Cloud of bleſſings, although at firſt it appeare but as the little hand of a man, yet in a ſhort time it ſpreads over the whole Heavens. When we fee the day begin to break, can we be ſo ſtupid as not to believe the Sun makes haſt in his courſe to ariſe upon our Horizon? When theſe things appeare, ſuch ſignes of the Times are given to us, what willfull ſins of ignorance ſhall we be guilty of, if we not minding them, believe not what is a coming? We can tell by the ſignes thereof, whether it will be faire weather, or ſoule, to day; And why are we ignorant of the ſignes of the Times? Surely it's a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of a hypocriticall ſpirit, whoſe damnation will be very great.</p>
            <p>Let none ſay, that which I ſeem to plead for, is encompaſſed about with ſuch infirmities, ſo much of the ſpirit of man, ſuch contrarieties to ſome Goſpel rules, as we cannot believe it to be of God: For this plea will be found no good plea at the Sons Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall, it's but a fond excuſe at beſt, lay what ſtreſſe you will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, it will not hold; This day, is a day of wrath, and the word ſpoken, is ſpoken in wrath, and except we dive into its glory, through the vailes of wrath upon it, and hearken to it, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, giving obedience to it, we ſhall periſh from the way of bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Againe, let us conſider the ſignes of this day of Chriſts coming to his <hi>Sion,</hi> that other Scriptures afford; and we ſhall find them
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170601:32"/>to be ſuch, as will ſignifie no ſuch thing to any, but to thoſe who have the moſt precious faith of this Goſpel, waiting for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the Holy Ghoſt will be upon them, and let them ſee the bleſſed fruit of their expectation: <hi>There ſhall come in the laſt dayes ſcoffers, walking after their owne luſts, and ſaying, where is the Promiſe of his coming? For ſince the fathers fell aſleep, all things conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue as they were from the beginning of the Creation,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.3. <hi>In heart ſaying, our Lord delayes his coming, ſmiting fellow ſervants; eating and drinking with the drunken,</hi> Mat. 24.48, 49. And though the Son of God hath told us, that his father will avenge his owne E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſpeedily, which cry day and night unto him, nevertheleſſe, <hi>When he comes, ſhall he find faith on earth?</hi> Luke 18.7, 8. yet, <hi>The Lord is not ſlack concerning his Promiſe</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. But is it not to this end? <hi>That the Tryall of your faith</hi> (the faith of Gods choſen) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much more precious then of gold that periſheth, though it be tryed with fire, might be found unto praiſe, and honour, and glory, at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.7. If theſe things be ſo, how ought we with all diligence, to walk with feare and trembling, leaſt we ſtumble and fall upon thoſe ſtumbling-blocks of wrath God throwes in the worlds way, and periſh upon them together with the world.</p>
            <p>And my Reaſons why I conceive the preſent Rulers of this world, are thoſe enemies of Chriſt, God will <hi>ſpeake to in wrath, and vex in his ſore diſpleaſure,</hi> are
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Becauſe I find the Scripture expreſly ſaith, That thoſe who ſhall be the Rulers of the world at this day of Gods ſetting his Son upon Sion, will oppoſe, and take counſell together againſt the Lord and his anointed;</hi> Therefore hath he ſaid, He will ſpeak to them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure, with ſetting his King upon <hi>Sion</hi> the hill of his holineſſe: And ſeeing it's a truth, that we are come to the dawning of the day, wherein the father will ſet his Son on his <hi>Sion;</hi> it muſt follow, that theſe are the Rulers that will be the ſubjects of the direfull diſpleaſure and wrath of the Great GOD.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Becauſe I perceive the Rulers are already taking Counſell together to make their hands ſtrong againſt the Lord and his anointed, and to break their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords from them;</hi> And the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Almighty God hath ſaid, He will then ſpeak to them in his wrath; and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure; and if they hearken
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170601:32"/>not to the Goſpel of the Kingdome preached to them, they ſhall without remedy periſh from the way of bleſſedneſſe; ſpeedy and ſwife deſtruction will be their portion. To prove this to the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar underſtanding is very hard; yet, if we will but conſider theſe few things, we may learne ſomewhat of the buſineſſe.</item>
                  <item>1 <hi>That the Characteriſticall worke of theſe Rulers, is not their acting, but TAKING CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCELL againſt the Lord and his anointed;</hi> (for, as it hath been already proved, God will not permit them to act their Counſells, but while they are in Counſell, he will ſpeak to them in his wrath.) Now, Counſell being a cloſe-cabinet act, though day may be diſcerned through a little cranny, yet, it's a hard work at preſent to prove it clearly to the underſtandings of others; but when they come to this height, have brought their Counſells (as they think) ready to put in execution, crying out for action, <hi>LET <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, &amp;c.</hi> then this will appear to be a truth, to thoſe that will not believe it now; and thoſe who now are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the fooles, uncharitable, raſh ſpirits of the Times, will be found guided by a ſpirit of wiſedome and truth.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>That theſe Rulers, not being tyed up by Satan or their owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and principles to any Rules of practice</hi> (all is left to their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and counſell) <hi>they will act ſuitable to the preſent intereſt of their ſtate and condition;</hi> Their bounds (in that reſpect) are larger to range in then ever any of the worlds Rulers had given them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; they will turne themſelves into any ſhape or form, to pleaſe men, to keep them within the bounds of their Rule and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; all this and much more, is couched under that ſignificant <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NSELL</hi> in the firſt Verſe of the Pſalme; they are well skill'd in the turnings and windings of the wylie Serpent, which practice of theirs makes things ſo dubious, and hardly diſcernable by the underſtandings of men.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>The preſent actings of theſe Rulers againſt ſome of the moſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſervants of our Lord Jeſus, ſignifies not a little to us concerning this matter:</hi> Conſider ſeriouſly (for it concernes us not a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o to doe) the true ground and reaſon of their ſo unworthy dealings with, and rough ſinfull handling of them: It weighs nothing, that theſe Rulers put an ugly Vizzard on their face, repreſenting them to the world, as cloven-footed (Devils) evill doers; for this hath been the courſe of Sarans inſtruments ever ſince the world began, thereby to depr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe the truth, that their falſhood and error
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170601:33"/>might take place: Herein theſe Rulers reſemble their predeceſſors, the Heathens and Kings of the earth; for which, they ſhall toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them and their Companions, be called to account ere long, when things will appear as indeed and in truth they are, not, as theſe Rulers would now have them: I ſay, let our hearts ponder the true reaſon of preſent actings, and we ſhall be ſenſible of the truth of the Aſſertion.</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Let us conſider daily, and make a narrow and thorow ſearch into the actions of theſe Rulers, with the naturall tendency of them;</hi> and get a Serpents wiſedome, with the innoceny of the Dove, and we ſhall not need that any man ſhould teach us in this matter.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe up this diſcourſe with one word to the Saints, the followers of the Lamb in theſe evill dayes.</p>
            <p>To you, the followers of your dear Lord Jeſus in this evill day of Apoſtacy: You have here, ſomething ſet before you of your work, God the father hath commanded you to doe, and your Lord (the Son) expects ſhould be done by you for him in this your day; alſo, the Qualifications hinted at, that will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able you to performe this work, according to the will and mind of your God and father. Further, you have it alſo hinted to you, that you are already entred into the confines of the work of this day; the Lord hath drawne over you to the view of the world (if they ſhut their eyes and will not ſee, the greater will their condemnation be) an Emblem of that ſtrange and glorious work, he is now about to performe, and bring to paſſe in the world: The waters of this Sanctuary are riſen almoſt to your ankles; Now give me leave to exhort you the boſome friends of our Lord Jeſus, <hi>Follow your Leader,</hi> the ſpirit of your Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, paſſe through and through the waters of the Sanctuary, that they may not onely waſh you to your ankles and knees, but to your loynes, all over; ſtay not your courſe till you come to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable overflowings of the ſpirit, that you cannot paſſe till you are taught to ſwim in that River of God, or after the example of your Lord to walk upon thoſe holy waters, doing the will of your God and father, and keep in the way of the promiſe and theſe things alſo ſhall be given you: <hi>Conſider your worke,</hi> and get an <hi>exact and diſtinct knowledge</hi> of that work your Lord and Maſter hath cut out for you to doe in this day of his Controverſie with the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170601:33"/>world and its profeſſing Rulers; and mind the Qualifications ordained to be beſtowed upon you to enable you to performe that great work to the praiſe and glory of grace.</p>
            <p>Let me (who am leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints, yet let me) beg of you theſe few things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Flee all flaſhineſſe and flagings of ſpirit;</hi> let not the predominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſuch infirmities over you, give the world occaſion to conceit; the ſword of the Lord in your mouths and hands ſignifies but a vaine flouriſh, is grounded on nothing but the airey fancies of men; but by a holy and ſteady perſeverance in taking up your Croſſe dayly, and following your Lord, give the world good ground to fear, that it's <hi>the ſword of the great God, wherewith he will plead with all fleſh,</hi> and <hi>the rod of his mouth, wherewith he will ſmite the earth,</hi> and <hi>the breath of his lips wherewith he will ſlay the wicked,</hi> Iſa. 11.4. Having put your hand to the Plow, look not back; having entred into the work, make not the leaſt retreat, now you are running out of her, over whom the Lords judgements and wrath are impending, which he will put in execution ere long, let not your hearts backſlide, <hi>Remember Lots wife,</hi> leaſt you alſo be turned into pillars of ſalt, made a ſavoury example of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and wrath of the great and jealous God, to work in thoſe that ſhall come after you a ſavoury ſpirit fit for the work you pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh from.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Get clear of this world;</hi> make a ſeaſonable and timely retreat into your Chambers (Gods hiding place) into the clefts of the Rock, that you may be hid from the wrath of God which is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon the world: Behold, the ſpirit of God himſelfe makes this Exhortation to you, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.20, 21. <hi>Come my people, enter thou into thy Chambers, and ſhut thy doores about thee: hide thy ſelfe as it were for a little moment, untill the indignation be overpaſt. For behold, the Lord cometh out of his place, to puniſh the inhabitants of the earth for their iniquity; the earth alſo ſhall diſcloſe her blood, and ſhall no more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her ſlaine.</hi> The Lord having told us what great changes and deſtructions he will bring upon the earth, gives us in theſe two verſes a loving invitation (with prevalent Motives) to hide our ſelves while that his great wrath be over-paſt: I ſay, <hi>Get clear of this world;</hi> our Lord tells us, <hi>It's impoſſible for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of heaven;</hi> for one whoſe heart is touched with and cleaves to the preſent evill world, to be an inheriter of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170601:34"/>world to come, which God hath promiſed as a reward to the faithfull followers of the Lamb: True, in this day you muſt ask a world, <hi>Heathens for an inheritance, and utmoſt parts of the earth for a poſſeſſion,</hi> but not this preſent world for your ſelves, but another for the Son, your Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; yet, for your comfort, know, you are not under an excluſion, for you muſt ask a world for Chriſt as he is your head, your King, that from him you may receive (according to the Decree of God) what your portion is, <hi>Of his fullneſſe you</hi> may and <hi>ſhall receive grace for grace:</hi> He that hath in this old world <hi>been faithfull over a few things,</hi> which the Lord hath given him in charge, <hi>ſhall in the</hi> (new) <hi>world to come, be made Ruler over many things, and enter into the joy of his Lord,</hi> Mat. 25.21. <hi>And every one that hath forſaken houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my names ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold, and ſhall inherit everlaſting life,</hi> Mat. 19.29. But he that doth not by the exerciſe of a faithfull ſpirit, make ſuch a retreat out of the world, ſhall periſh in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of this world. If our ſpirits be right, the counterpaine of the ſpirit of our Lord in this day, our prayer to our God and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will be for the utter diſſolution of this old world, and the bringing forth the new Heavens and new Earth promiſed; for the performance of thoſe glorious and admirable Promiſes, which the God and father of our Lord Jeſus hath made concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Now if our hearts be not wholly taken off this preſent evill world, that voyce, <hi>Come out of her my people,</hi> will ſeem to us (as the ſpeech of righteous <hi>Lot</hi> to his Sons in Law) as the ſpeech of one that mocketh, and not hearkening to it, we ſhall periſh with the world; at beſt, if any ſuch temper'd ſoule be ſaved, it will be as by fire, he will ſuffer great loſſe: What advantage then can the enjoyment of this preſent evill world be unto us?</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Take not up your reſt in any attainment;</hi> though you may have taken many a ſtep in following your Lord, and gotten on high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the world, and (it may be) the reſt of your brethren, yet take not up your reſt there, but keep on your pace (endeavouring daily to mend it) in following the Lamb; be not contented nor ſatisfied with any thing below the ſitting downe together with your Lord and Saviour at the right hand of glory, in thoſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the fathers houſe, which your Lord is gone before to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for you, and hath promiſed to come againe to receive you,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170601:34"/>that where he is you may be alſo; Reſt not untill you ſee your Lord (the Son of man) ſit in the Throne of his glory, and then ſhall you ſit upon Thrones alſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28. I ſay, take not up your reſt in any attainment, otherwiſe, you will be of the number of thoſe firſt which ſhall be laſt, in <hi>verſ.</hi> 30. Thoſe that are lag now, will get before you to your great regret of ſpirit; and (as in the next Chapter) a part of thoſe many which be called, but not cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to the work of the day, and ſo you will run a great hazard of miſſing that glorious reward, the gift of your Lord, <hi>To raigne together with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Remember this, <hi>That in this day, in the carrying on the work your Lord hath put into your hands, there muſt be no guile found in your mouth, you muſt be without fault before the Throne of God:</hi> Your Lord expects you ſhould exerciſe ſuch ſincerity of ſpirit in your following him in this work, as that you be not defiled with any of that guile (that hypocrifie and doubleneſſe of heart and tongue) the worlds mouth hath alwayes been filled with: In the matters of the Kingdome of your Lord, and his out-goings againſt the world in this day, you muſt be without guile, and without fault, ſo clear, as that God ſitting on his Judgement Throne may ſee no fault in you, <hi>without fault before the Throne of God:</hi> Let it be ſo, and when your Lord comes, you will hear his bleſſed voyce calling unto you, <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſervant, enter thou into the joy of thy Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 Would you be ſuch, as God will teach knowledge, and make knowne his mind to, in ſuch a day of wrath as this is, <hi>Then</hi> (it's not my counſell but the Lords) <hi>be weaned from the milke, and drawne from the breaſts.</hi> Iſa. 28.9. <hi>Whom ſhall be teach knowledge? and whom ſhall be make to underſtand doctrine?</hi> (or the ſtammeringe of lips (as the margent hath it) at this day) <hi>them that are wean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the milke, and drawne from the breaſts?</hi> Be yee weaned from the milk of the worldly carnall profeſſing Church, be drawn from the breaſts of her conſolation, and the Lord will teach you know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and make you to underſtand doctrine; there ſhall not be a ſtammering of the lip, in the things of God, in this your day, but the Lord will make you acquainted with it, to the underſtanding of it. Inſtead of her milk and her adulterous breaſts, he will give you the teachings of his good ſpirit, making you intimately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his bleſſed everlaſting Goſpel: Though, he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from the worldly profeſſing Church, that his word is but
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170601:35"/>
               <hi>here a little, and there a little</hi> among them (as he formerly dealt with the carnall, yet profeſſing Church of <hi>Ephraim</hi>) though his word hath been among them, <hi>precept upon precept, precept upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and line upon line, line upon line,</hi> but now, it's but <hi>here a little, and there a little,</hi> the Lord is gotten to the threſhold off their houſe, and is departing quite away from them; I ſay notwithſtanding this, he will manifeſt himſelfe to you, if you be weaned from their milk, and drawne from their breaſts; ſeparate your ſelves from, have nothing to doe with the worldly (though profeſſing) Church, he that hath made this Promiſe, will performe it, for he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; let who can, charge him in the leaſt with the breach of any tittle of his word and promiſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Be upon your watch, that you let not ſlip the nick of time God gives you to (and he expects you ſhould) doe your worke in.</hi> The time when God expects you ſhould receive his Son, and exalt him among you as your King, is then, when he is rejected by the worlds (refined) Rulers, and they enter into Aſſociations &amp; Combinations againſt him, to break his bands aſunder, and caſt away his cords; this is the time for you to ſtand up and declare for the Decree of God the father on the behalfe of your Lord and Saviour; and, the very nick of time, which you are not upon your perill to let ſlip, (as you will anſwer before his father and your father) is then, when theſe wicked (yet profeſſing) Rulers are going about to execute their abominable Counſells, crying <hi>LET <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, let us</hi> doe it, <hi>break his bands, and caſt away his cords,</hi> then, it's your work and duty to ſtand up and cleave to your King, follow him whitherſoever he will lead you: I ſay, ſlip not your time, for it concernes you, if you will not owne him now before the world (you will run a deſperate hazzard that) he will not owne you before his father, and then, what miſery and unhappineſſe will betide you? Let your owne enlightned conſciences judge.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Beware of unbelief, the mother of all evill and miſery;</hi> though you ſhould get to the very borders of the land of Promiſe, and the providence (the voyce) of God call you to encounter with your enemies, to remove every let and obſtruction in the way to your full poſſeſſion, yet unbelief is able to drive you back into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe againe, if you take not great heed; would you not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to your wilderneſſe Companions, the <hi>Bryars,</hi> and the <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles?</hi> would you not have that mournfull ditty heard in your
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170601:35"/>mouths againe? <hi>Woe is me that I ſojourne in Meſech, that I dwell in the Tents of Kedar,</hi> then flee all unbelief that mortall enemy of your happineſſe: unbelief of the truths and myſteries of the Sons Kingdome, is the <hi>Characteriſticall ſin</hi> of the times immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the coming of Chriſt, <hi>When he comes ſhall he find faith on earth?</hi> This interrogation is a ſtrong affirmation of the truth of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, <hi>He ſhall not find faith on earth.</hi> The Son had in the preceding words aſſerted the faithfullneſſe of God in the certainty of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging his Elect which cry day and night unto him; yet, ſaith he, <hi>Nevertheleſſe, when the Son of man cometh, ſhall be find faith ou earth?</hi> In that time when God is about to ſpread abroad his faithfullneſſe in making bare his arme, to anſwer all the cryes and prayers of his people, to avenge them of their enemies, yea, even when the Son of man is a coming to make good the word of his bleſſed father, <hi>Shall be find faith on earth?</hi> That is, <hi>He ſhall not find faith on earth:</hi> Men will not believe that it's the time of Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming his Promiſes; the face of things appear ſo (through the counter-working of the evill one, the man of ſin and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) to the meerly rationall eye, that in this very time when the Son of man is coming to avenge the Elect of God which cry day and night unto him, the men of the world become mockers, ſaying, <hi>Where is the Promiſe of his coming, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the Creation?</hi> And others that would be eſteemed the better ſort, they cry out, <hi>The time is not come, The time is not come;</hi> They believe not the word of the Kingdome. Beware of this unbelief, leaſt you looſe the comfort of this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Son, when other faces ſhine with the joyes of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yours be bedew'd with teares, the ſad fruit of this defiling unbeliefe.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
